上帝未死2
坚 固 你   肖恩・哈珀   演唱
"Hold You Up"    Shane.Harper   singing
你曾坚信的真理，开始遭受瓦解逼迫
?When it's coming apart,you had it all?
这还不止
?It wasn't enough?
是的，还远不止
?No, it's not enough?
他们告诉你，不值得如此去I卫真理
?They tell you，it's not worth the price
那就弃之真理不顾好了
?So just let it go?
但你知道你不能
?But you know you can't?
你知道你也不会这么去做
?You know you won't?
虽困难重重，不，还要为真理竭力争辩
?It's not easy, no， finding the words to say?
当你感到迷失时，你会寻找到神为你开的道路
?When you're feeling lost,you'll find your way?
这世界是如此的支离破碎，留给你的有时仅是冷漠
?The world is so broken and sometimes it leaves you cold?
在夜间你感觉不到亮火,真光来引导你归家
?At nighttimes you can't feel the fire to guide you home
魔鬼会伤害你，试图偷盗你所知的真理
?The demons will harm you and try to steal what you know?
但神所差派的天使帮助你脱离遭害
?But the angels,they brought you?
他们前来坚固你
?And they're gonna hold you up?
他们来坚固你
?They're gonna hold you up?
他们看到了你眼中的惧怕
?They see the fear in your eyes?
千斤重担如压心头
?Heart sinks like a stone?
因你惧怕，重压你灵魂
?Cause when you're afraid,it weighs on your soul?
时候将到，你就会知晓
?When the timing is right,somehow you'll know?
无人能站立得住，无人能靠自己站立得住
?When nobody stands,stand on your own?
虽困难重重，不，还要为真理竭力争辩
?It's not easy, no,finding the words to say?
当你感到迷失时，你会寻找到神为你开的道路
?When you're feeling lost,you'll find your way?
这世界是如此的支离破碎，留给你的有时仅是冷漠
?world is so broken and sometimes it leaves you cold?
在夜间你感觉不到亮火来引导你归家
?At nighttimes you can't feel the fire to guide you home
魔鬼会伤害你，试图偷盗你所知的（真理）
?The demons will harm you and try to steal what you know?
但神所差派的天使帮助你脱离遭害
?But the angels,they brought you?
他们前来坚固你
?And they're gonna hold you up?
他们来坚固你
?They're gonna hold you up?
- 名字？- 惠顿，乔什.惠顿.
- Name?- Wheaton. Josh Wheaton.
你的预登记表带着吧？
You got yourpre-registration sheet?
是的
(Josh)Yeah.
所有的核心要求是都在这上面
All core requirementsare here.
你的人文选修课如何？
What is yourhumanities elective?.
选哲学150
Philosophy 1 50.
雷迪森，周一、周三和周五早上的11：00
Radisson, 1 1 :00 on Monday,Wednesday, and Friday.
你可以考虑选择另外的讲师
You might want to think abouta different instructor.
因为？
Because?
我们只能说你游荡掉到蛇坑
Let's just say you'rewandering into the snake pit.
我推荐你帕特尔或者穆勒
I'd recommend Patelor maybe Mueller.
算了吧，哥们，这选课不能说不好吧
Come on, man.It can't be that bad.
想想古罗马的斗兽场，
Think Roman Colosseum,
还有狮子，人们正在欢呼你的死亡
lions,people cheering for your death.
哦，但我不得不重新安排我的整个计划了
(Josh)Yeah, but I'd have torearrange my whole schedule.
我不认为，我真的要――
I don't thinkI can really--
这是你的葬礼
It's your funeral.
最后的截止日期是22日
Last drop dateis the 22nd.
你需要谨记这一点
You might want tokeep that in mind.
你的手续已经办完了
You're done.
- 谢谢- 没事，预祝有个好学期
- Thanks.- Yeah, have a good semester.
- 嗨.- 马丁.叶
- Hi.- Martin Yip.
P.R.C.代表什么？
What doesP.R.C. stand for?.
中华人民共和国
People's Republic of China.
呵呵.真的吗？
Oh. Seriously?.
哦，是的，我是认真的
(Martin)Oh yes,always serious.
好的
(registrar)Okay.
跟我开什么玩笑啊！
You've gotta be kidding me!.
- 怀特.沃尔夫（公司），有什么需要帮忙的？
(receptionist)White & Wolfe,how can I help you?.
是的，请稍等
Yes, please hold.
怀特.沃尔夫（公司）
White & Wolfe.
好的，我会告诉他们你致电过
Mm-hmm, I will let 'em knowyou called.
谢谢，再见
Thank you, bye-bye.
- 枥木重工股票（日本 ）
(businessman)Buy as muchTochigi Heavy lndustries
满仓买进
as you can on-margin.
我们已经得到了一个合并的消息
We've gotten wind of a merger
而日本人并不十分关心内幕交易
and the Japanese could care lessabout insider trading.
我保证，你会因此而感谢我的
You're gonna thank mefor this one, I guarantee it.
你是在与马克（通话）
You're on with Marc.
嘿，我需要你给我指明方向
Hey, I need youto give me directions.
你是在开玩笑吧？
You're kidding, right?.
不是的，有人偷了我的GPS导航仪
No, somebody stole my GPS
我手机上的时间决定了我开车只能像开直升飞机那样快了
and my phone has decided thatit is spinning propeller time.
你不用那么做，日经指数才刚刚开盘
(Marc)Can't do it.The Nikkei just opened
有一个特大单抛售正在继续
and there's a massivesell-off going on.
还有，顺便说一下，我为只有我们的星期五
Oh, and by the way, I madereservations for us Friday
在巴黎左岸预订了行程
at La Rive Gauche.
等一下，你会带我巴黎左岸
Wait, you'll take meto La Rive Gauche
但你不会花时间给我指明方位？
but you won't take the timeto give me directions?.
我有什么好处？
What's in it for me?.
你在开玩笑吧？
You're kidding, right?.
你是认真的
You're serious.
好吧，好了，我在去突击采访
Okay, well, I'm on my wayto an ambush interview
鸭司令-威利・罗伯逊的路上
of Duck CommanderWillie Robertson,
而且我要冲进聚会
and I am going tocrash that party
留住他风风火火的脚步
and hold his feetto the fire.
昨天的网络点击量已经超过32000次
And yesterday's discreteweb hits were over 32,000,
这意味着我这个月有超过了一百万的浏览量
which means I am on pace forover a million views this month
和我 -
and my--
[在一起]- 自己的广告客户
[together]--own advertisers.
这才是我的女孩！
That's my girl!
不只是有一个漂亮的脸蛋
Not just anotherpretty face.
谢利小姐，我准备了一些特别的东西给你
Miss Shelley, I've got somethingspecial for you today.
想你会喜欢它
Think you're gonna like it.
噢，我的鸡肉！
Oh my, chicken!
我都不知道我上次吃鸡肉是什么时候了
I don't know when wasthe last time I had chicken.
昨天的午餐和晚餐也是这样的
That would be yesterday,for lunch and dinner.
你是认真的？
Are you serious?.
我不认为她应该每（天）重复同样的事
I don't think that she shouldhave the same thing every--
你认为还有其他事情让她感到快乐？
You think of anything elsegonna make her that happy?.
我能帮忙吗？
Is it okay if I help?.
哦，好吧，好吧
Oh, alright, alright.
你是新来的，不是吗？
You're new here,aren't you?.
是我，妈妈
It's me, Mom.
米娜，你的女儿
Mina, your daughter.
对不起，我认不出
I'm sorry, I don't--
没关系，没关系
It's okay, it's okay.
我没有看到一个戒指.
I don't see a ring.
情况有点复杂.
It's complicated.
我是雷迪森教授，这是哲学150
I am Professor Radissonand this is Philosophy 1 50,
介绍哲学思考
Introductionto Philosophical Thought.
如果下面任何一项消息是你的事实情况
If either of those factsis news to you,
那么你还是现在趁早离开这里
then now would beyour turn to leave.
据我所知
I understandsome of you are here
有人是为了满足自己的文科选修学分要求（而选此课）
to satisfy your Liberal Artselective requirements.
如果你正在寻找一种简单的而且是没多少功课的班级
If you're looking foran easy grade without much work,
那么你还是现在趁早离开这里
well, then now would beyour turn to leave.
看，你现在就读于一所大学
See, you've now enrolledat a university.
你将会被布置大学水平的功课
You'll be expected to produceuniversity-level work.
很好，我也走了
Pfft, I'm out.
总有一些人
There's always one.
米歇尔・福柯、伯特兰・罗素
Michel Foucault,Bertrand Russel,
路德维希・费尔巴哈、贝尔托・布莱希特
Ludwig Feuerbach,Bertolt Brecht,
弗里德里希・尼采、安・兰德、乔治・桑塔耶拿
Friedrich Nietzsche,Ayn Rand, George Santayana,
德谟克里特斯、狄德罗、戴维・休谟
Democritus,Denis Diderot, David Hume,
约翰・穆勒、阿尔贝・加缪、理查德・道金斯
John Stuart Mill,Albert Camus, Richard Dawkins,
西格蒙德・弗洛伊德、诺姆・乔姆斯基博士
Sigmund Freud,Noam Chomsky.
这样的例子不胜枚举
The list goes on.
哲学家，诗人，科学家，作家
Philosophers, poets,scientists, authors,
他们都是学术界的泰斗
towering intellects,all of them.
但他们都有什么共同之处?
But what do theyall have in common?.
好的
Yes?.
他们都过世了
They're all dead.
嗯，这是不正确的
Well, that would beincorrect.
道金斯先生和乔姆斯基先生
Mr. Dawkins and Mr.Chomsky
- 依然非常活跃在他们的专业领域，先生 -
arestill very much alive, Mister
（名叫）G-dog Gerard Trigga.
G-dog Gerard Trigga.
G-dog
G-dog.
还有其他人（回答）？
Anyone else?.
没有人？
No one?.
好吧，在世或过世的他们都是无神论者
Well, they are,or were...atheists.
第6世纪的法文"athe'isme,"
Based on the 1 6th-centuryFrench "athe'isme,"
是来源于希腊文 "theos"，意思是“上帝”
from the Greek "theos,"meaning "God,"
和前缀"a"演化而来
and from the prefix "a,"
在希腊文中"a"的意思就是“没有”
meaning, as it alwaysdoes in Greek, "without."
总之，每一个我写过名字的思想家
In short, each ofthe thinkers I named
强有力的回击了，这世界是没有上帝的
took the strong positionthat there is no God,
作为相对的弱势地位不可知论
as opposed to the weak positionof agnosticism.
诺斯替主义（"Gnostic"），来源于希腊语诺斯"gnosos"，所谓的“知”
"Gnostic," from the Greek"gnosos," to know,
又一次，带有前缀“a”的意思是不知道的，
and again, with the prefix "a"meaning to not know,
或者更准确地说，怀疑（宇宙中）一个至高无上的（上帝）存在
or more accurately, to doubt theexistence of a supreme being.
这学期，我建议大家拒绝
This semester,I propose that we refuse
浪费我们有限的时间在一起辩论（上帝）的存在
to waste our limited timetogether debating the existence
一个天空中的大男人，一个仁慈的神话
of the big man in the sky,the myth of a benevolent,
全能的，超自然的存在
all-powerful,supernatural being.
- 嘿！- 你的航程怎样？
- Hey!.- How was your flight?.
- 精彩.- 精彩？
- Wonderful.- Wonderful?.
这就像一次30个小时的飞行
It's likea 30-hour flight.
36小时
Thirty-six.
很乐意见到你
Great to see you.
很高兴认识你
Nice to see you.
达喀尔飞往苏黎世，苏黎世到法兰克福
Dakar to Zurich,Zurich to Frankfurt,
8小时的停留
an 8-hour layover,
而后直飞至卡特国际机场
and directto Carter lnternational.
唉，那精彩这词该如何诠释呢？
Ugh, how does that translateas wonderful?.
我很高兴，我很安全，现在我在这里，因上帝是良善的.
I'm happy, I'm safe, and nowI'm here because God is good.
一直
All the time.
一直？
And all the time?.
上帝是良善的
God is good.
上帝死了
God is dead.
当然，这是一个比喻，
This is, of course,a metaphor,
但一个说明性的意义，不是说上帝已经死了
but an illustrative one meaningnot that God has somehow died,
而是k从来没有首先存在
but rather that he neverexisted in the first place,
只是超出了我们祖先能想像的到而已
other than in the depthsof our forebears' imaginations.
k在过去的时代是一个有用的童话
He was a useful fairy talein ages gone by,
k的烈怒被用来解释的瘟疫发生
when his fiery anger was usedto explain away plagues
和农作物歉收，疾病和灾害
and crop failures,diseases and disasters,
我们现在所归诸于细菌和病毒
which we now ascribeto bacteria and viruses,
染色体疾病，和板块构造
chromosomal disorders,and plate tectonics.
总之，是科学和理性取代了迷信
In short, science and reasonhave supplanted superstition,
这一切都变得更好
and we areall the better for it.
经过你们的许可后
And with your permission,
我想我们一起绕过这种虚无的辩论
I would like to bypass thissenseless debate all together
而直接跳到结论
and jump to the conclusion
你们每一个大二学生都应该意识到
of which every sophomoreis already aware of:
其实上帝不存在
there is no God.
我要求你们每一个人
All that I requirefrom each of you
就是刚才我让诸位填写的文件
is that you fill inthe papers I've just given you
有三个小字：“上帝死了”
with three little words:"God is dead,"
请签上你的大名
along with your signature.
我们越快达成一致共识，
The sooner we reacha unanimous consensus,
这是我所期望的
which I expect we will,
我将避免那些枯燥、
I will be sparedthe tedious duty
争论不止的乏味论点
of slogging throughdry and dusty arguments,
你将绕开部分课程
and you will bypassthe section of the course
当你接受这些传统
in which studentshave traditionally received
可以获得这学期的最低等级分数
their lowest gradesof the semester.
当你签完字后，请把纸放右边
And when you finish, pleasepass your papers to the right.
谢谢
Thank you.
呵呵，一个小写的“g”
Oh, a lower case "g."
也许这一个应得到额外的学分
Maybe this oneought to get extra credit.
谢谢
Thank you.
对不起，先生 -
Excuse me, Mister--
惠顿乔什.惠顿
Wheaton.Josh Wheaton.
惠顿先生，有什么问题吗？
Mr. Wheaton,is something wrong?.
是的，我不能
Yeah, I can't.
我不能做你想要我做的
I can't dowhat you want.
我是一个基督徒
I'm a Christian.
呵呵，别担心.
Oh, don't worry.
你仍然可以回到你的宿舍里
You can still go backto your dorm room
曲膝
and sink to your knees
在你的床边祷告，如果你愿意的话
and pray to your bedsideif you'd like.
你在你的个人生活做什么，那是你的事情
What you do in yourpersonal life is your business,
但你在课堂上做什么，是我来管.
but what you doin this class is mine.
我不能.
I can't.
好吧，惠顿先生.
Alright, Mr. Wheaton.
请允许我解释下替代选择.
Allow me to explainthe alternative.
如果不让你自己在教室上承认
If you cannot bring yourselfto admit that God is dead
上帝已死
for the purposes of this class,
那么你将要至I卫上帝并没有死
then you will needto defend the antithesis
这个对立面上
that God is not dead.
而你需要做的是站在这个教室的
And you'll need to do itin front of this class
讲台这里
from the podium.
如果你失败了，你不得不失去本次机会
And if you fail, as you shall,you will fail this section
而且你立即失去你期末成绩的30%
and lose 30% of your final graderight off the bat.
你准备好接受（挑战)吗？
Are you readyto accept that?.
好的，那谁能决定我是否赢
Well, who would decidewhether I won
或者输了这场辩论
or lost the argument?.
没事，我可以
Well, I would.
这是我的课堂，我的规则
It's my class, my rules.
分级是我的特权
Grading's my prerogative.
我没有不尊重你，但我不确定你可以做到很客观
No disrespect, but I'm not sureyou can be objective.
你有何建议
What would you propose?.
那么，他们怎么样
Well, what about them?.
嗯，这很有趣
Well, that's interesting,
但为什么想要我授权给他们？
but why would I wantto empower them?.
好了，你已经赢了他们.
Well, you've alreadywon them over.
我的意思是，我必须让不信服的他们，
I mean, I'd have tounconvince them,
让他们承认他们错了.
get them to admitthey were wrong.
好吧，惠顿先生.
Alright, Mr. Wheaton.
你将拥有3次的辩论机会
You'll get 3 sessions,
接下来3堂课的最后20分钟
the last 20 minutesof each of the next 3 classes,
投放你的案例
to make your case.
我保证我的干扰会降到最低
I promise to keepmy interruptions to a minimum.
你可以在课堂上采用任何你喜欢的问题
You may take whatever questionsyou'd like from the class,
但我不会增加分配给你的时间
but I will not increaseyour allotted time.
当然，你要完成
Of course,you'll be responsible
布置给你的所有其他课堂作业
for all the otherclass assignments.
不过，你知道，你可以改变你的想法
But, you know,you could change your mind
在下节课带来你签过名字的声明
and bring in your signedstatement at our next class,
我们将往前看，当这件事情没发生过一样
and we'll go forward as thoughnone of this ever happened.
我们其余的人,已经除去了原始的迷信
The rest of us, having dispensedwith primitive superstition,
将我们的焦点转向在现实世界的问题
will turn our focus tothe issue of being in reality.
关于我们下一堂课，
For our next class,
请务必先预习下戴维・休谟的《归纳法问题》
please have read David Hume's"The Problems of lnduction"
和勒内・笛卡儿（法国哲学家、数学家、物理学家)的《方法论》
and Renee Descartes'"Discourse on Method,"
阁下可能添加伯特兰・罗素
to which you may addBertrand Russell's
“为什么我不是基督徒”
"Why I Am Not a Christian"
准备到惠顿先生的讲座中
in preparationfor Mr. Wheaton's lecture
感谢他的失败，以帮助我们实现
and in thanks for hisfailure to help us reach
一致的共识
a unanimous consensus.
我明白，你不想否认你的信仰
You don't want to denyyour faith, I get it.
所以，答案很简单：降级
So, the answer's simple:drop the class.
是的，但我不确保我能做到这一点
Yeah, but I'm not sureI can do that.
我感觉上帝希望有人为他卫道.
I feel like God wantssomeone to defend him.
别傻了.
Don't be ridiculous.
我不知道，我只是不停的思考
I don't know,I just keep thinking
C.S.刘易斯的信条（英国20世纪著名的文学家，学者，杰出的批评家，公认的二十世纪最重要的基督教作者之一）
of that C.S. Lewis line,
真正的危险，是考验一个人信仰真实与否的试金石
"Only a real risk cantest the reality of a belief."
所以，因此你要把我们未来会发生的危机，也对之相对比
So, you're gonna risk our futureover your yearbook quote?.
乔什，我为什么在这里？
Josh, why am I here?.
你好，欢迎回到地球，乔什
Hello, earth to Josh.
我为什么，我们在毕业班毕业时曾致词过
Why am l, Salutatorianof our graduating class,
这里是我的第三选择志愿学校？
here at mythird-choice school?.
对不起，我有在未来50年
I'm sorry for havingthe next 50 years
关于我们生活的计划了
of our life planned out.
这就是真正的我
That's just who I am.
我不知道，凯拉 ，只是
I don't know, Kara,it's just--
乔什，我爱你，但是我绝对不许你
Josh, I love you,but I absolutely forbid you
在教授自己的课堂上去反对他
to go up against this professorin his own classroom.
这对我们是利益攸关的
We have too much at stake.
整个事情的操纵手段，使你看起来像一个白痴
The whole thing's riggedto make you look like an idiot,
如果你想进入法学院，
and if you wantto get into law school,
你这门课一定不能不及格
you can't affordto flunk this class.
甚至一个“C”可能也是灾难性的
Even a "C"could be disastrous.
我不知道你为什么穿高跟鞋
I don't know whyyou wear those heels.
这双鞋有什么问题吗？
What's wrong with 'em?.
你太高了，你比我高了
You're too tall.You're taller than me.
你是男人，足以应付它
You're man enoughto handle it.
我只是说，我不希望在舞会是矮个
I'm just saying, I don't wantto be the short guy at the prom.
罗伯逊先生！
Mr. Robertson!
嗨，或者我应该叫你威利？
Hi, or should lcall you Willie?.
你可以叫我威利
You can call me Willie.
艾米.瑞安，“新左派”是我的博客专栏
Amy Ryan,I blog "The New Left."
我可以问你几个问题吗？
Can I ask youa few questions?.
当然可以,说吧, 这是我妻子―
Yeah, sure, fire away.This is my wife--
科丽，我知道了
Korie, I know.
实际上，在这里看到你，我很惊讶
I'm actually surprisedto see you here.
我以为你在回家，赤着脚，还怀孕
I thought you'd be home,barefoot and pregnant.
我没有赤脚，孕妇已经过去了很长一段时间
I haven't been barefoot andpregnant in a really long time.
我还挺怀念那些日子，是吧？
I do kindamiss those days, huh?.
是啊，你要开始再次？我们可以试试
Yeah, you want to startagain?. We can try.
不
No.
你已经赚了一笔销售设备
You've made a fortuneselling devices
那些旨在吸引水鸟至它们死亡
that are designed to lurewater fowl to their deaths.
哦，我当你说想“你”
Oh, I guesswhen you say "you,"
你指的是我的全体家人
you're referring to thewhole group of my family,
这将是“你”
which would be "y'all."
你可以只将其更改为“你们”
You can justchange it to "y'all."
这会是一个更简单的表达
That'd be aneasier expression,
这样，大家都在那里了
that way it'll geteverybody in there.
所以，你们都已经发了财，是不是啊？
So, y'all have madea fortune, isn't that right?.
我们正在做的还不错
We're doing alright.
我们可以买的皮车卡还是大轮胎
We can certainly buybigger tires on our trucks
四轮驱动，不会陷在泥地里
and four-wheelersto get out in the mud with,
所以生活是美好的
so life is good.
是什么让你认为，你有道德权利
What makes you thinkyou have the moral right
四处残害和杀害无辜的动物？
to go around maiming andkilling innocent animals?.
嘿，看看，让我们弄清楚一件事
Hey, look, let's just getone thing straight.
我不是残害什么
I ain't maiming nothing.
无论我看到、我瞄准和我射击
Whatever I see and I aim at,I shoot.
当我射击后，我杀了它，然后我吃了它
When I shoot it,I kill it and then I eat it.
所以，你就杀了那些鸭子？
So, you do killthose ducks?.
当然，我这样做了.我该怎么办呢？
Of course I do.What am I gonna do,
当要煮它们的时候，它们还在动？
cook 'em while they'restill moving around?.
这才是残酷的事情
That would be cruel.
那就糟糕了
That'd be bad.
那么，这不是一种（杀戮）行为？你确实为你所做的感到自豪？
So, this isn't an act?. You'reactually proud of what you do?.
我当然如此感觉.我如果不感到自豪我为什么怎么做？
Of course I am. Why would ldo it if I'm not proud of it?.
那么，你认同他所说的每件事？
And you go alongwith everything he says?.
我们已经结婚20年
We've been marriedfor 20 years.
他说的每件事，我并非都认同
I don't go alongwith everything he says,
但在重要的事情上，是的
but on the thingsthat matter, yeah,
我完全赞同
I agree wholeheartedly.
那么，对那些在节目中被你冒犯的人，你要说些什么？
So, what do you say to peoplewho are offended by your show,
不仅仅是因为狩猎
not just becauseof the hunting,
而是因为你在每一集中公开向耶稣祷告?
but because you openly prayto Jesus in every episode?.
嘿,我们没有试图去冒犯任何人,好吗?
Hey, we're not tryingto offend anybody, alright?.
如果他们不想看这节目，他们可以换频道
If they don't want to watch theshow, they can turn the channel.
至于我向耶稣祷告
As far as mypraying to Jesus,
我的人生和我所有的全部都属乎上帝
my life and my whole eternitybelongs to God.
所有这一切都是暂时的：金钱，名利，成功
All this stuff is temporary:the money, fame, success.
暂时的
T emporary.
甚至人生也是暂时的
Even life is temporary.
耶稣，才是永恒的
Jesus, that's eternal.
耶稣（在圣经）这样说：
Jesus said this:
凡在人面前认我的，
"Whoever acknowledgesme before men,"
我在我天上的父面前也必认他（太10：32）
he will acknowledgebefore the Father in heaven.
凡在人面前不认我的，我在我天上的父面前也必不认他.（太10：33）
"Whoever disowns me,I'll disown him to the Father."
这些经文很重要，现在是用红字标注的
Now, those words are writtenin red so they're important.
就是这样？
And that's it?.
就是这样.这就是我们要讨论的
That's it.That's what we're going with.
很简单，不是吗？
Pretty simple, isn't it?.
感谢您的宝贵时间
Thanks for your time.
来吧，让我们做一些确认
Come on, let's godo some acknowledging.
欢迎你加入我们的行列
You're welcome to join us.
不，谢谢，我很好.
No thanks, I'm good.
你很好？
You're good?.
好吧.
Alright.
那位女士是谁？
Who was that lady?.
你非常美
You're beautiful.
我希望你不要这么做
I wish youdidn't have to do that.
为了我的父亲，他非常保守的
It's for my father.He's very traditional.
你和谁说话？
Who were you talking to?.
没有人
No one.
阿依莎，我知道活在他们的世界里很难
Ayisha, I know it's hardliving in their world
而且还要与此分离
and being apart from it,
一个你能看，却不可触碰的世界
a world you can seebut can't touch.
我知道他们看上去很快乐
I know they seem happy,
但要知道，当你环顾周围所有的人
but know that when you lookaround at all those people,
没有一个人在敬拜上帝
there is no onewho worships God,
不是他应受和要求的敬拜方式
not the way he deservesand demands to be worshipped.
我们不能忘记我们是谁，我们该做什么
We must never forgetwho and what we are.
这是最重要的事情
That is the mostimportant thing.
是的，爸爸
Yes, Baba.
我只坚持这一点，因为我爱你
I only insist on thisbecause I love you.
你知道的，不是吗？
You know that, don't you?.
我爱你？
That I love you?.
当然，爸爸
Of course, Baba.
你需要帮忙吗？
Can I help you?.
你在等人？
You waiting for someone?.
是的，你可以这么说
Yeah, you could say that.
看起来，在这一刻，k好像出去了
It looks like he'sout at the moment.
好吧，那可能就是k派遣我来的原因吧
Well, maybethat's why he sent me.
[Stellar Kart singing "一和零"]（基督流行朋克乐团）
[Stellar Kart singing"Ones and Zeros"]
我们是一和零
?We are the onesand zeros?
美丽而不完整
?The beautiful incomplete?
我们是未来的勇士
?We are the future heroes?
一场暄丽多彩的交响乐
?A colorful symphony?
我们就是那些人
We are the ones
我本可放弃这门课，跑开
I could drop the class,run away,
假装什么都没有发生
pretend likeit never happened,
这就是我的女朋友想要的
which is whatmy girlfriend wants.
我可以在纸上签署我本不相信的事
I could sign the paper sayingsomething I don't believe.
或者我要在现场观众面前犯学术自杀
Or I commit academic suicidein front of a live audience
是为了试图证明上帝存在
by trying to provethat God exists.
选这门课的人有多少？
How many peoplein that class?.
可能80个
Eighty maybe.
他们当中有多少人，你认为
And how many of themdo you think
曾在这里停留过脚步
would everstep foot in here,
或在其它任何教会
or any other churchfor that matter?.
好吧，也许没有
Well, none probably.
所以，你接受了这个挑战，
So, your acceptanceof this challenge,
假如你决定接受它，
if you decide to accept it,
唯一能较为深入接触到上帝和耶稣的机会
may be the only meaningfulexposure to God and Jesus
他们却没曾有过
they'll ever have.
是啊
Yeah.
是的，我也是怎么想的
Yeah, I suppose so.
请查阅马太福音10:32-33
Check outMatthew 1 0:32-33.
什么，这是这些？就这样？
What, that's it?.That's all?.
是的
Yeah.
只是一个圣经引用？
Just a Scriptural citation?.
如果你查阅上述经文后，还是犹豫不决
If you're still undecidedafter that one,
请看路加福音12:48
Iook at Luke 1 2:48.
这不可能如此简单
It can't be that simple.
当然可以
Sure it can.
你在这里，因为在你里面还有微小的声音
You're here because thatstill small voice inside you
对别人想要你做出的选择感到不开心
isn't happy with the choiceseveryone else wants you to make.
就我个人而言，我认为这是圣灵与你说话
Personally, I think it's theHoly Spirit talking to you.
如果我们不消灭圣灵的感动，k会一直作催促感化的工作
That's how he interacts with usif we allow him to.
所有你需要做的就是决定
All you have to dois decide
你是否愿意听从
whether or notyou're willing to listen.
这不容易，却很简单
It's not easy,but it's simple.
凡在人面前认我的，
"So everyone whoacknowledges me before men,
我在我天上的父面前也必认他；（马太福音10：32）
"l also will acknowledge beforemy Father who is in heaven,
“凡在人面前不认我的，
"but whoeverdenies me before men,
我在我天上的父面前也必不认他.（马太福音10：33）
I also will deny beforemy Father who is in heaven."
惟有那不知道的，
"Everyone to whommuch was given,
做了当受责打的事，必少受责打.
"of him much will be required,
因为多给谁，就向谁多取；
"and from him to whomthey entrusted much,
多托谁，就向谁多要.（路加福音12：48）
they will demand the more."
对不起，我迟到了
Sorry I'm late.
我必须处理好一大堆事，才能来这里
I had to move a ton of stuffaround just to get here.
没事
That's alright.
请坐，瑞恩小姐
Please, go and have a seatMs. Ryan.
哦，对不起，第二次了
Oh, excuse me a second.
我们根据你上星期的化验单得到了诊断结果
We've gotten your results backfrom your test the last week.
好吧，我是说 -
Okay, as I was saying--
我很抱歉，这个电话我必须要接
I'm so sorry.I have got to take this call.
艾米
Amy.
你的化验单显示是阳性
Your resultscame back positive.
你得了癌症
You have cancer.
我没时间治疗癌症
I don't have timefor cancer.
我太忙了
I'm too busy.
听着，癌细胞已经扩散到周围组织
Listen, it's already growninto the surrounding tissue.
你的淋巴结有感染，你的血液标志物
Your lymph nodes are involvedand your blood markers indicate
也有向远处转移的证据
evidenceof distant metastasis.
现在，我已经为你排好了 核磁共振检查
Now, I've alreadyscheduled you for an MRl.
我们需要确定它（癌细胞）扩散的程度
We need to determinethe extent of it.
我知道你很重要
I know you'revery important
这世界没有你，将无法正常运转
and the world can'tget along without you,
但是我的工作是让你知道
but it's my jobto let you know
那可能会确切的发生在你身上
that it may be preparingto do exactly that,
当然，除非你立即开始治疗
and it certainly will unlessyou begin immediate treatment.
你明白吗？
Do you understand?.
嘿，宝贝
Hey babe.
宝贝，你去哪里了？你手机关机了？
Babe, where've you been?.Did you turn your phone off?.
更像我忘了手机开机
More like I forgotto turn my phone on.
你知道今天是什么日子？
Do you knowwhat day it is?.
周四？
Thursday?.
还有别的？
Anything else?.
第13？
The 13th?.
周年快乐
Happy anniversary.
六年前，你我的青春触碰
Six years ago, your youth groupcollided with mine.
你想起来了吧
You remembered.
嗯，嗯，我们要庆祝一下
Mm-hmm, andwe're gonna celebrate.
你还记得我们是怎么认识？
You remember how we met?.
因为 Newsboys 乐队（现代摇滚乐团）
The Newsboys.
下周五他们会在镇上
They're gonna bein town next Friday.
你让我太惊喜了，这就是为什么我爱你
You are amazing,which is why I love you.
听我说，我知道我昨天的处理方式太过强势
Look, I know I came off probablyway too strong yesterday.
你知道，我只是 -
You know, I just--
我担心一些外面的事进入我们的生活
I get concerned when outsidethings start coming between us.
你懂我的意思，是不？
You get that, can't you?.
- 当然- 原谅我？- 永远
- Sure.- Forgive me?.- Always.
来吧
Come on.
我只是需要 -
I just need--
哇！
Whoa!
好吧，那总不会都是统计学吧
Well, that can'tall be Statistics.
乔什，请告诉我，你没有一直
Josh, please tell meyou haven't been spending
花时间在哲学上面
all your timeon that philosophy thing.
不是所有的（时间）
Not all of it.
好的，大部分时间
Okay, most of it.
乔什，这不好笑
Josh, that's not funny.
好吧，这真的不是
Okay, it's really not.
听我说，这是我想做的事，好吗？
Look, this is somethingI want to do, okay?.
我不知道我之间怎么了
I don't understandhow it comes between us.
乔什，你所做的一切是要关于我们的
Josh, everythingyou do is about us.
好吧，我们是一个团队
Okay, we're a team.
我的意思是，我们在做什么，6年到永远，对不？
I mean, we're what, 6 yearsgoing on forever, right?.
那意味着你的成绩，你的整个未来
That means your grades,your whole future,
我是其中的一部分
I'm a part of that.
我不明白这能使我们的未来受益？
I don't see how thisis contributing to our future.
那，即没有我的父母
Yeah, well,neither do my parents
也没有我生命中的其他人
or anyone else in my life.
该怎么告诉你呢
What should that tell you
是不是每个人爱你的人
if every single personthat loves you
都要说完全一样的事情？
is sayingthe exact same thing?.
乔什，我正在让你知道现在要为自己考虑
Josh, I'm letting you know nowfor your own good,
这个实验已经结束
this experiment is over.
你需要优先考虑和决定
You need to prioritizeand decide
谁是你生命中最重要的人，
who's the most importantperson in your life,
我还是雷森迪教授？
me or Professor Radisson?.
如果我的选择是上帝
What if it's God?.
上帝要你和我在一起，所以这是相同的答案
God wants you with me,so it's the same answer.
把书还给图书馆，在那张愚蠢的纸上签上字
Return the books to the library,sign the stupid paper,
然后向前行
and move on.
从现在开始一年之后，我们回头看这些，只会想笑
A year from now, we'lllook back on this and laugh.
我们已经不是在高中了
We're not inhigh school anymore.
你现在作出的决定能有真正的后果
The decisions you make nowcan have real consequences.
乔什
Josh!
乔什，这挺严重的
Josh, this is serious.
我知道
I know.
你知道
You know.
我不能相信,我要开12小时的车程到佛罗里达是为了做一些
I can't believe I'm makinga 12 hour drive to Florida
我12岁时会做的一些事
to do things that seemedcorny when I was 1 2.
大卫，我答应给我母亲一张我在米老鼠耳朵中的照片
David, I promised my mothera picture of me in mouse ears
而且还是站在童话城堡前的
standing in frontof the fairy tale castle.
我呢站在米老鼠耳朵中，照片是给她的
The mouse ears are for me,picture is for her.
对你来说，这是旧帽子，但对我来说，却是梦想成真
T o you, it's old-hat, but to me,it's a lifelong dream come true.
你难道不能理解吗？
Can you notunderstand that?.
然后我们就去坐潜艇到海底
Then we'll go forthe undersea submarine ride.
事实上，我觉得他们好像在20年前就把设施关闭了
Actually, I think they closedthat ride like 20 years ago.
然后我们将乘坐世界上最大的过山车
And then we'll ride theworld's biggest roller coaster.
第16大
Sixteenth biggest.
在我的脑海里，当我们下降时而尖叫
In my mind, whenI'm screaming as we descend,
这将是世界上最大的
it will bethe world's biggest
我会很高兴，（我认为最大）不是因为它的高度
and I'll be glad thatit's not taller than it is.
这听起来有点问题
That doesn't sound good.
是不是因为电池问题 -
Maybe the battery--
或许发动机
Or the starter.
无论是那样坏了，我们现在去不了任何地方
Either way, we're notgoing anywhere right now.
我会打电话并安排汽车租赁的
I'll call and arrangefor a rental car.
但是，我们怎么拿到所租的车？
But how will weget to the rental car?.
他们把车给我们送过来的
They'll deliver it to us.
你说真的？
Are you serious?.
是的，肯定
Yeah, absolutely.
他们会把我们要开的车给送过来的？
They'll deliver usthe car we are to drive?.
是的
Yeah.
喂？
Hello?.
太有意思了
Amazing.
但也有一些家伙在那里
But there are someflat-earthers out there
还仍然认为存在一个至高的上帝
who still consider theexistence of a supreme deity
要么必要的，要么不言自明的，或者两者兼而有之
to be either necessary,or self-evident, or both.
正如先前所宣布那样
And with that,as previously announced,
我要把讲台让给惠顿先生了
I will be turning the podiumover to Mr. Wheaton,
谁将呈现案例赞同
who will be presentinghis case in favor
（宇宙)存在一个至高无上的独裁者
of a supremecelestial dictator,
也被称为上帝
otherwise known as God.
惠顿先生，你准备好了吗？
Mr. Wheaton,are you ready?.
讲台是你的
Podium is yours.
无神论者说，没有人能证明上帝的存在
Atheists say that no onecan prove the existence of God,
是的，他们是对的
and well, they're right.
但我是说没有人能反驳上帝的存在是虚假
But I say no one candisprove that God exists.
但辩论这个问题的唯一途径
But the only wayto debate this issue
是看现有的证据
is to look atthe available evidence,
这就是我们要做的
and that's whatwe're going to do.
在判断上帝（是否存在）事上
We're going toput God on trial,
由雷森迪教授担任检控官
with Professor Radissonas the prosecutor,
而我作为辩护律师
and meas the defense attorney,
而你们都是陪审团
and you as the jury.
大多数宇宙学家都认同
Most cosmologists now agree
我们的宇宙起源于137亿年前
that the universe begansome 1 3.7 billion years ago
称为宇宙大爆炸事件
in an eventknown as the Big Bang.
那么，让我们来看看理论物理学家
So, let's lookat theoretical physicist
和诺贝尔物理学奖得主史蒂芬.温伯格关于
and Nobel Prize winnerSteven Weinberg's description
宇宙大爆炸的描述
of what the Big Bangwould have looked like.
而且因为他是一个无神论者
And since he's an atheist,
我们能肯定在他的描述中
we can be surethere isn't any believer-bias
没有任何信仰倾向
in his description.
起初发生了一个大爆炸
In the beginning,there was an explosion,
在最初3分钟里
and in 3 minutes,98% of the matter there is
形成了宇宙中98%的物质
or ever will be,was produced.
我们曾有一个宇宙
We had a universe.
已有2500年
For 2,500 years,
大多数科学家同意亚里士多德的思想
most scientists agreedwith Aristotle on the idea
一个稳定状态的宇宙
of a steady-state universe,
宇宙一直存在
that the universehas always existed
没有起始，也没有结束.但圣经不同意此观点
with no beginning and no end,but the Bible disagreed.
在20世纪20年代，比利时天文学家乔治・勒梅特，一位有神论者
In the 1 920s, Belgian astronomerGeorges Lematre, a theist,
他其实是-
who was actually also--
什么是有神论者？
What's a theist?.
有神论者是那些相信上帝存在的人
A theist is someone who believesin the existence of God.
他说，整个宇宙横空出世
He said that the entire universejumping into existence
在万亿分之万亿分之万亿分之一秒
in a trillionthof a trillionth of a second,
自虚无至
out of nothingness,
不可思议的强烈闪光发出
in an unimaginablyintense flash of light
这就是他对宇宙形成的回答
is how he would expectthe universe to respond
假如上帝确实在创世记1:3发出命令
if God were to actually utterthe command in Genesis 1 :3,
“要有光.”
"Let there be light."
换句话说，宇宙的起源开始呈现
In other words, the originof the universe unfolded
读创世纪后，确实会如上所述
exactly how one would expectafter reading Genesis,
在2500年间
and for 2,500 years,
圣经始终是正确的，科学却曾发生谬误
the Bible had it rightand science had it wrong.
好么，你最早能在5点钟赶到这里？
So, the earliestyou can get here is 5?.
好吧，我们会在这等你
Okay, we'll be waiting.
等等，它有空调，对不对？
Wait, it hasair conditioning, right?.
好的，谢谢.
Okay, thanks.
嗯，看来我们直到今晚也不会到达那里
Well, looks like we won'tget there 'til late tonight.
对不起，我想你错过了整整一天在（迪士尼)公园的时间
Sorry, I think you're gonnamiss an entire day at the park.
这没关系，大卫.
It's okay, David.
我敢肯定，我们今天可以好好利用在这里的时间
I'm sure we can make good useof our time here today.
当然可以与唱诗班负责人交通
Sure.
我们
We can meetthe choir director,
为即将演唱的音乐会一起选择歌曲
talk about song choicesfor the upcoming concert.
或者我们可以见一下姐妹团契
Or we could meetthe women's club
探讨下一个手工艺品（教堂）义卖的细节
about the detailsfor the next craft bazaar.
很多重要的东西
Lots of important stuff.
还有，趁你还没离开
And since you're not leaving,
你还有时间和米娜一起吃午饭
you'll have timeto meet Mina for lunch.
对了，我还能和米娜一起吃午饭
Right, I can meetMina for lunch.
听起来，你比我好像更需要这个假期
Sounds like you need thisvacation more than I do.
不，我只想做一些有意义的事情
No, I just need to dosome meaningful work
这样我才能过好这个假期
so that I can have somethingto take a vacation from.
你应该知道，我们做的一些最重要的事情
You know, some of the mostimportant work that we do
对我们来说，或许意义不大
may seem meaningless to us.
像那些传教士一样
This comingfrom the missionary
在（属灵的）战壕中真真切切的
who literallyis in the trenches,
每日为上帝赢得新心
winning hearts for the Lordon a daily basis.
大卫，上帝会差派你到k预备你去的地方
David, God has youexactly where he wants you.
k的信实也在每一件细小的事情上
He who is faithfulin a very little thing
当然在大事也同样信实
is also faithful in much.
上帝知道你正在做的事情
God knowsyou're doing the work.
这也是k宏伟计划的一部分
It's all partof his grand design.
所有这些都指向有一个上帝创造了它（宇宙）
All of which points to a Godthat created it.
你看，在现实世界中，我们从来没看到事物
You see, in the real world,we never see things
由无有到存在
jumping into existenceout of nothingness,
但无神论者希望在这规则上做些小例外
but atheists want to make onesmall exception to this rule,
即宇宙和其上的一切本就存在
namely, the universeand everything in it.
但在他的著作《上帝错觉》
But in his book,"The God Delusion,"
理查德・道金斯如此述说：
Richard Dawkins says
假如你告诉我，是上帝创造了宇宙
that, "lf you tell meGod created the universe,
那么我就有权利问你是谁创造了上帝
then I have the rightto ask you who created God."
道金斯的议题才有意义
Dawkins' questiononly makes sense
按照谁创造了一位上帝（逻辑）
in terms of a Godwho has been created.
对于非受造的上帝来说是没有意义的
It doesn't make sensein terms of an uncreated God,
这就是基督徒所信仰的上帝
which is the kind of Godthat Christians believe in.
甚至在方程式中把上帝替换
And even leaving Godout of the equation,
我也有权利把道金斯先生的问题
I then have a right to turnMr. Dawkins's own question
还给他，询问他
back around on him and ask,
假如宇宙创造了你，那么谁创造了宇宙？
"lf the universe created you,then who created the universe?. "
你看，无论是有神论者和无神论者都背负
You see, both the theist andthe atheist are both burdened
回答同样的问题
with answeringthis same question
关于物质的起源
of how did things start.
我希望你能领悟到
What I'm hopingyou'll pick up from all this
你没必要先把知识给扼杀掉
is that you don't have tocommit intellectual suicide
再去相信创造主背后的创造
to believe in a Creatorbehind the creation.
在某种程度上，你根本不允许有上帝
And to the extentthat you don't allow for God,
你会很难找到一个可令人难以信服的
you'd be pretty hard-pressedto find an incredible
另外解释：物质是如何产生的
alternative explanationfor how things came to be.
好的，我能想像你对自己刚才说讲的很满意
Well, I imagine you'requite pleased with yourself.
我看到你在小心避免史蒂芬・霍金这个人
I see you've carefully avoidedthe fact that Stephen Hawking,
世界上最有名的科学家
the world's mostfamous scientist,
还有他也不是一个有神论者
and who is not a theist,
最近出来赞同一个自我设计的宇宙
has recently come out in favorof a self-designing universe.
我没有回避，我只是没有 -
I haven't avoided it,I just didn't--
你只是不知道这件事.
You just didn'tknow about it.
嗯..好吧，让我们来看看霍金教授，
Alright, well let's seewhat Professor Hawking,
这位剑桥大学的“卢卡斯”物理教授（为剑桥大学的一个荣誉职位，授予对象为数理相关的研究者，同一时间只授予一人）
Lucasian Professor of physicsat Cambridge,
占据了由艾萨克・牛顿爵士曾持有的头把教学椅
who occupies a teaching chaironce held by Sir lsaac Newton,
不得不说一下宇宙的起源
has to say aboutthe origin of the universe.
那么，我引述下：“因为万有引力等定律，
And I quote, "Becausethere's a law such as gravity,
宇宙可以并会从无到有，自发形成.
"the universe can and willcreate itself from nothing.
自发创造可以解释
"Spontaneous creationis the reason
宇宙中并非无物存在、
"there is somethinginstead of nothing.
为什么宇宙存在以及为什么我们存在.
"It's why the universe exists,why we exist.
这就没必要借助上帝在其中
"lt is not necessaryto invoke God
来推动宇宙的运转
to set the universein motion."
引述完毕
End of quote.
那么，你可以从来没有发现过他的论点
So, you may have nevercome across his comment,
但他的观点依然存在
but his point remains.
你怎么回答？
How do you answer?.
我不知道
I don't know.
你不知道？
You don't know?.
我把你整个论点给推翻了
I prick the balloonof your entire argument
只用了一个很简单的方式，你不知道吗？
with a single pin,and you don't know?.
呵呵
Huh.
嗯，我的意思是：我想告诉你我有完美的答案
Well, I mean, I'd like to tellyou I have the perfect answer,
但它不会动摇我最基本的信心
but it doesn't shakemy underlying faith.
好了，因此那些在历史中最伟大科学们的思想
Okay, so the greatest scientificmind in all of history says
上帝不是必要的,但 一个大一新生在第一学期说：
that God is not necessary, buta first-semester freshman says,
“哦，是的，k是.”
"Oh, yes he is."
哇，你知道，那会是一个真正艰难的选择
Wow, you know, that's gonnabe a really tough choice.
好吧，我期待在下周的讲座（与大家再见）
Well, I look forwardto next week's lecture.
下课
Class is dismissed.
你认为你比我聪明，惠顿？
Do you think you'resmarter than me, Wheaton?.
你认为你提出的任何论点
Do you think there'sany argument you can make
我不会有一个答案？
that I won'thave an answer for?.
我从来没有说过我比你聪明
I never saidI was smarter.
这是你迄今为止说过最为有智慧的话
That's the firstintelligent thing you've said.
现在，我想明确这一点
Now, I want tomake this clear.
在那个教室里，有一个神，
In that classroom,there is a god,
是的，我就k
and yep, I'm him.
我也是一个忌邪的神，所以不要试图羞辱我
I'm also a jealous god,so do not try to humiliate me
在我的学生面前.
in front of my students.
你知道，我还调查了你所申报的专业
You know, I also checked upon your declared major.
法律预科？
Pre-law?.
法律预科究竟是什么？
What exactly is pre-law?.
那个东东我们不授予学位的
We don't awarddegrees in that.
不要打扰我的回答，但你要知道这一点
Don't bother answering,but know this,
假如你真的还想继续这猜字谜游戏
if you truly feel a needto continue with the charade,
我将通过我个人的努力
I will make it my personalmission to destroy any hope
把你未来的法律学位扼杀掉
of a law degreein your future.
祝你有美好的一天
Have a nice day.
- 你做了，不是吗？- 什么？
- You did it, didn't you?.- What?.
你知道我在说什么.
You know whatI'm talking about.
你去了， 而且还辩论，不是吗？
You went and did yourargument, didn't you?.
是的，是我做了
Yeah, yeah I did.
你想去证明什么？
What were youtrying to prove?.
我甚至不能用言语来形容
I'm not even surethere are words to describe
我现在的感受
what I'm feeling right now.
对不起乔什，我们俩之间结束了
I'm sorry Josh,but it's over between us.
就这样？刚刚- 已经结束了？
That's it?.It's just--it's over?.
一切都结束了，乔什.
It's over, Josh.
如果你继续做这些愚蠢和自私的事
If you're going to do somethingthis stupid and selfish
我其实已经告诉你将会发生什么
after I already told youwhat would happen--
是的，那件事是有道理的，不是吗？
Yeah, but that's sort ofthe point, isn't it?.
这一点对我来说却很重要，对吧
This is something that'simportant to me, right,
不过对你来说却并不重要
but since it's notimportant to you,
你在我们中间只设置了成功与失败的选项
you made it a make-it-or-break-it-thing for us.
你没问我，你只是告知我
You didn't ask me,you told me.
这不是一个我们做出的决定
It wasn't a decisionthat we made,
这不是一个你为我们俩共同做出的决定
it was a decision thatyou made for the both of us.
那么，总要有人去做（决定）
Well, somebody had to.
好
Okay.
就这样？ “好”？
That's it?. "Okay"?.
这不是我想要的
It's not what I want.
老实说，我仍然希望你会改变你的想法，好不
Honestly, I'm still hopingyou'll change your mind, right,
这件事，我必须要去做
but I have todo this thing.
我总感觉是上帝呼召我去做（这件事）
I feel like it's somethingthat God wants me to do.
我不能转身逃离，尤其是现在，更不行
I can't just turn away from it,especially not now,
现在，我已经开始做了
now that I've started.
关于你，我母亲说的太对了
My mother wasso right about you.
我只希望我能听到一丝有意义的话
I just wishI'd had the sense to listen.
拯 救 生 命  演唱    Manic Drive 乐队 (福音摇滚乐队)
Manic Drive singing "Save a Life"
想象下，一个刚刚年满8岁美丽的小女孩
Oh picture it, a little girl,just a beautiful 8-year-old
试图在这疯狂的世代中苦度此生
Trying to live throughthis life in a crazy world
嘿，法赫德
Hey, Fahid.
她发现自己已是一个青少年她的生活处于毁灭中
She finds herself as a teenand her life in ruins--
告诉女孩她的人生意义和目的
Showed that girl she hadmeaning and a purpose to life
为了避免她沉沦
o b
你会向她宣扬真理，还是任其活在谎言中
Would you tell her the truthor let her live in a lie?.
这一切都可以改变
It all just seems to change
当你所见时，你要去拯救失丧的生命
When you see itas a life to save--
（讲道）哥林多前书（15章3节）经文
(preaching)1 Corinthians saysyou're saved,
基督照圣经所说，为我们的罪死了，
and Christ died for our sinsaccording to the Scriptures,
而且埋葬了，又照圣经所说，
that he was buried, that hewas raised on the third day
第三天复活了
according to the Scriptures.
如果你真心相信
If you believe thisin your heart,
如果你凭信心接受
if you accept this by faith,
要知道，上帝会赦免你的过犯，（用宝血）洁净你
you see, God will forgive you,he'll cleanse you,
在真理里得自由释放  [葛福临(Franklin Graham)证道]
and he'll set you free.
给我！
Give me that!
你千万不要告诉爸爸
You must never tell Baba.
对我发誓，你永远不会说什么
Swear to meyou will never say anything.
发誓！
Swear it!
拿瓶 Cristal到我的桌子
Bottle of Cristal,my table.
是的，谢利先生
Yes, Mr. Shelley.
我有一些消息
I have some news.
我也是
Me too.
好吧，还是我先吧
Okay, but me first.
我刚刚被任命为合伙人
I've justbeen named partner.
我想我得了癌症
I think I have cancer.
你听到了吗？
Did you hear me?.
你听到我刚才说什么吗？
Did you hearwhat I just said?.
我得了癌症
I have cancer.
这不能等到明天（再讲）？
This couldn't waituntil tomorrow?.
什么？
What?.
你怎么可以这样说我？
How can yousay that to me?.
我想你是爱我的
I thought you loved me.
是的，但你改变了我们的约定
I do, but you'rechanging our agreement,
你破坏了我们之间的协议
you're breaking our deal.
你让这听起来像一个合同谈判
You make it sound likea contract negotiation.
那么，你认为这是什么？
Well, what did youthink this was?.
我认为这是爱情
I thought it was love.
长大点吧，艾米
Grow up, Amy.
爱在英语语言是最被滥用的词
Love is the most overused wordin the English language.
我们想要的一些东西的时候，会说这话
It's what we saywhen we want something,
当我们需要一些东西
when we need something,
你也应该跟其他人一样感到内疚才是
and you're as guilty of itas anybody.
我们在一起挺有乐趣的
We had fun.
你是我狂热，年轻的女友，还有份别致的工作
You were my hot, younggirlfriend with the chic job.
我是你引导你进入上流社会、迷人、成功的男友
I was your upwardly mobile,charming, successful boyfriend.
我们在一起，因为我们彼此
And we were togetherbecause we each got something
在这关系上得到了想要的东西
out of the relationshipthat we wanted,
这很好
and it was good.
这是 -实际上，也挺让人满意的
It was--actually, it was great.
不过，现在这些都已经结束了
But now it's over.
我怎么没发现你是这样的人？
How did I notsee this in you?.
因为你只看到你想看到的
Because you sawwhat you wanted.
你明白我可能会死吗？
You understandthat I might die?.
我只能说，对此我很遗憾
And I'm sorry about that.
嘿，你是我哲学课的同学
Hey, you're inmy philosophy class.
马丁，对不？
Martin, right?.
正确，那么你是乔什先生
Correct,and you're Mr. Josh.
是啊
Yeah.
是啊，这就是我，乔什先生
Yeah, that's me,Mr. Josh.
嘿，那些都在我们的阅读清单上吗？
Hey, is that onour reading list?.
不是的
No.
我可以问你一个问题吗？
Can I ask youa question?.
好的，当然可以
Yeah, sure.
为什么你要做你正在做的那些事？
Why are you doingwhat you are doing?.
其他的人都认为我疯了
Everyone elsethinks I'm crazy.
我的女友 -前女友为这事离开我
My girlfriend--ex-girlfriend left me over it.
我的父母也不希望我去冒这个险
My parentsdon't want me to risk it.
在这一切结束时
At the end of it all,
在接下来的学期中
I'm gonna have towork like a dog
我必须要忙得像条狗一样
for the rest of the semester
只是为了让我的其他课能赶得上
just to catch upon my other classes.
你描述你目前的困难
You have describedyour difficulties,
但你还没有回答我所问的问题“为什么”
but you haven't answeredmy question of why.
我不知道
I don't know.
我只是 - 我认为耶稣是我的朋友
I just--I think of Jesusas my friend.
那么，你觉得耶稣是上帝？
So, you think Jesus is God?.
是的，是上帝的儿子
Yeah, and the Son of God.
我不想令他失望
I don't wantto disappoint him,
即使每个人都认为我应该---
even if everyonethinks I should.
看，对我来说，他并没有死
See, to me,he's not dead.
k一直活着
He's alive.
我不希望任何人被劝服不相信k
I don't want anyone to gettalked out of believing in him
仅仅是因为一些教授认为他们应该（这样）
just because some professorthinks they should.
回头见，马丁
See you around, Martin.
再见
Bye.
你好，汤姆・布兰查德，美罗城汽车（公司）
Hiya, Tom Blanchard,Metro City Auto.
这是你的钥匙
Here's your keys.
- 谢谢- 保证（让您）满意
- Thank you.- Satisfaction is guaranteed.
我是否需要签什么字？
Do I need to sign something?.
那肯定要的，我正在把一辆车给你
Absolutely.I'm giving you a car.
在这里签字
Sign here,
然后在那里签个字，那里再签个字
and then one more right there,and one more there.
你也可以在这三个地方仅用首字母签名
And if you could just initialthere, there, and there.
谢谢
Thank you.
当你回来给我们打电话，你这个周末可以拥有它
Call us when you're back.You have it for the weekend.
我们到时会来跟你办交收（手续）
We'll come pick you up.
谢谢
Thanks.
你没有跟我开玩笑吧
You're kidding.
你做了什么？你把它弄坏了？
What did you do?.Did you break it?.
什么？
What?.
检查，看看它是否还挂着档
Check and seeif it's still in gear.
没有，在停车档
No, it's in park.
我搞不明白，它5分钟之前还能动的
I don't understand.It worked 5 minutes ago.
好了，那么，现在真的不行
Alright,well, now it's not.
你们多久才能把另一辆车给我们？
How soon can youget us another car?.
不过，今晚真的不行了
Well, not tonight.
现在已经过了下午5：30了
It's already after 5:30.
大家都回家了
Everyone's gone home
我今晚的试镜会晚到一点
and I'm already kind of latefor an audition.
试镜？
An audition?.
是啊，那帮家伙和我正在排练“推销员之死”
Yeah, the gang and lare doing "Death of a Salesman"
有几分像晚宴剧场差不多
and it's kind ofa dinner theatre thing.
“保证满意”成了什么了？
What happenedto satisfaction guaranteed?.
没事，大卫.我们可以明天启程
It's alright, David.We can leave tomorrow.
是你想开这真趟车的，而且已经错过了半天？
You want to make this driveand miss half the day?.
也许将会下雨呢
Perhaps it'sgonna rain anyway.
预测明日温度华氏82（摄氏28度），上午9点会阳光明媚
Forecast for tomorrowis 82 and sunny at 9 a.m.
有时候你很通情达理
Sometimes youdon't make any sense.
有时候你太在乎
Sometimes you make too much.
请记住，上帝是良善的
Just remember, God is good.
一直
All the time.
一直？
And all the time?.
上帝是良善的
God is good.
请你帮忙签下字拒绝接收这辆车吧？
Will you sign thissaying you reject the car?.
你是在与马克（通话）
You're on with Marc.
是我，白痴，你的妹妹
It's me, dork,your sister.
哦，怎么了？
Oh, and this is about?.
你真的应该去看看妈妈
You reallyshould go see Mom.
她并不怎么好
She's not doing well.
她不怎么好已经好多年了
She hasn't beendoing well for years.
这就是为什么他们称之为老年痴呆症
That's why theycall it dementia.
不过，你还是应该去看看她
Still, you shouldgo see her.
克莱尔说你已经很长一段时间没去那里了
Claire said you haven'tbeen there in awhile.
这有什么关系啊
Like it matters?.
还有，我刚刚给她买了台新电视机
Besides, I justbought her a new TV.
听我说，我跟你达成一个交易
Look, I'll make you a deal.
你去，问她3+3等多少
You go and you ask herwhat 3 + 3 equals.
如果她能说出正确答案，我会去看她的
If she gives you theright answer, I'll visit.
这不公平
That's not fair.
生活本就是不公平的，我要挂电话了
Life's not fair.I gotta go.
帮我向艾米问声好
Say hi to Amy.
不行，我跟她已经结束了
No, that's over.
你做了什么？
What'd you do?.
不能解决的个人问题
Unresolved personal issues.
她得到了一些东西，她也要学会去经历
She's got some stuffshe's gotta work through.
我很遗憾听到这个消息
I'm sorry to hear that.
好吧，就是这样
Well, that'sthe way it goes.
好了，我们开始吧？
Okay, ready toget this started?.
说真的，你应该要有自己的生活
Seriously, youhave got to get a life.
是啊，请告诉我
Y eah, tell me about it.
嘿，亲爱的
Hey honey.
哦，对不起，门是开着的
Oh, sorry,the door was open.
我只让自己进来了哦
I just let myself in.
- 嗨- 嗨
- Hi.- Hi.
嘿，我要的那瓶葡萄酒拿了伐？
Oh hey, did you pick upthe bottle of wine I wanted?.
我拿了
I did.
我把它落在车上
I left it in the car.
它是在车上
It's in the car.
不用担心它
Don't worry about it.
你已经花很多时间在准备就餐了
You have a loton your plate.
所以，你知道，只是 -
So, you know, just--
非常感谢你帮我们准备好了晚宴
thank you for helpingset up our dinner party.
好了，除非我错了
Well, unless I'm wrong,
所有的客人都是哲学系的？
all the guests are fromthe philosophy department?.
还真不是，薇薇安是一个社会学家
That's not true.Vivian's a sociologist.
你证明了我的观点
You're proving my point.
你看，我其实帮不了忙
Look, I can't help it.
你看，我在你身边的时候
See, my intellectual rigorfalls to pieces
我的理性掉了一地
the instantI get around you.
真的吗？
Really?.
你肯定在逗我玩
You could have fooled me.
我第一次走进教室时
The first time I walkedinto your classroom,
你是满有血性与冲劲
you were allblood and thunder.
那只是一个表演，很大程度上只是为了吸引你
That was a performance,staged largely for your benefit.
在此同时，我一直试图让我的眼睛离开你
In the mean time, I kepttrying to keep my eyes off you
并希望有这个漂亮的脑袋里充满了智慧
and hoping that there wasa brain inside that pretty head.
为什么呢？
Why?.
嗯，因为，如果没有，那么，你知道，
Well, because if there wasn't,then, you know,
我没有办法让自己和你一起出去
there's no way I could havemade myself go out with you.
你知道的，正因为如此，我一直等到你以高分通过期中考试
Look, as it was, I waiteduntil you aced the midterm.
这是一个A减
It was an A-minus.
很接近了
Close enough.
来吧，她去那里了
Come on, where is she?.
咦？
Huh?.
谁？
Who?.
那无忧无虑，自由奔放的女孩
That carefree,free-spirited girl
我几乎冒着自己的职业生涯风险跟她约会的那位
who forced me to almostrisk my career by dating her.
你知道，是那位在引述艾米莉・狄金森（美国传奇女诗人）、雪莱
You know, the one who quotedEmily Dickinson, and Shelley,
和海绵宝宝时都保持同样自信的她
and Spongebob Squarepantswith equal self-confidence.
我的意思是，在过去的米娜身上发生了什么呢？
I mean, what ever happenedto the old Mina?.
因为我很想念她
'Cause I miss her.
她的母亲正在一天天衰残
She has got a momwho's failing,
她感触到时间在飞奔流逝
she's sensingtime is passing by,
并且她开始怀疑与他是非能同负一轭
and she's starting to wonderif she's unequally yoked.
那么，是不是又读了一遍（圣经）？
Alright, you've beenreading again, haven't you?.
读经、听道、思想
Reading, listening,thinking.
你很难称之为思想
You can hardlycall this thinking.
事实上，它是站在思想的对立面的
As a matter of fact,it's the opposite of thinking.
你知道我是一个基督徒
You know I'm a Christian.
你第一次开始看到我时其实就知道了
You knew that whenyou first started seeing me.
是的，但你也知道我不是
Yes, and you knowthat I'm not.
是啊，我知道，
Yeah, I know,
我知道有很多东西
and I knowthere's a lot of things
你不想去谈
you don't wantto talk about,
所以我们不谈论它们
so we don'ttalk about them.
是啊，除了从静默开始变得越来
Yeah, except the not talkingis starting to get louder
越响，后来很快就会震耳欲聋之外
and louder, and soonit will be deafening,
我也不知道我是否可以忍受
and I don't knowif I can put up with that.
- 我知道- 你呢？- 是啊
- I know.- Do you?.- Yeah.
因为我们需要明确这一点
Because we needto be clear on this.
在这个房间里只有我们两个人的关系
There's only roomin this relationship for two,
这意味着我不去找一个情妇
which meansI don't get a mistress
你也不要拖着2000多岁的死木匠不放
and you don't get to drag a2,000-year-old dead carpenter
把流动的拉比变成我们的生活
turned itinerant rabbiinto our lives.
就这样吧，我要去梳洗一下
Look, I'm gonnago freshen up.
这是同一辆车？
Is this the same car?.
哦，不，先生不，先生
Oh, no sir.No, sir.
同一型号，不同的颜色.
Same model,different color.
另一辆是赤霞红
The other onewas a cabernet.
这是云母红色
This is moreof a merlot.
你知道，说谎可不好
You know,lying's not good.
骗一位被按立的牧师，就是彻头彻尾的坏
Lying to an ordained ministeris flat-out bad.
你知道的，对吧？
You know that, right?.
先生，我向你保证，这是确定是一辆不同的汽车
Sir, I assure you this isa different automobile.
（钥匙）在这里，试下吧
Here, try it out.
你试镜试的怎么样了？
How'd your audition go?.
呵呵，还不错
Oh, pretty good.
我打算扮演“比夫”所以 - 谢谢你的关心
I'm up for the role of Biff,so--thanks for asking.
你们要去哪里？
You guys going somewhere?.
你要担任系主任职位的那个事情怎么样了？
How's it look for you withthe department chair position?.
这学期期中将会复审
I'm up for reviewmid-semester.
鲍威尔院长向我保证这是一个扣篮（系主任职位属我）
Dean Powell assures meit's a slam dunk.
不错，恭喜了，杰弗里
Well, congratulations Jeffrey.
什么都在你的盘子里（掌控之中）？
Anything elseon your plate?.
并不是的
Not really.
可否分享下？
Feel like sharing?.
在我本学期的入门课程中有这样一位学生
I've got this student in myintroductory class this semester
那个谁---好吧他采取了挑战（措施）
who's--well,he's taken a challenge
为了证明上帝的存在
to provethe existence of God.
在您的课堂上？
In your classroom?.
- 是的.- 傻小子
- Yes.- Silly boy.
- 大一新生？- 是的
- Freshman?.- Oh yeah.
我觉得这似乎很不公平
Doesn't seemquite fair to me.
那么，那会是怎样的？
Well, how's that?.
他在讲台上是缺乏经验的
He's inexperiencedin front of a room,
而你希望他与你竞争
and you're expecting himto compete with you
在自己的专业领域
in your own fieldof expertise.
得了吧，米娜，这对我来说很有趣
Come on, Mina.This is fun for me.
如果一个男孩想让自己出丑还有学术自杀
I can't help it if a boywants to make a fool of himself
我也是爱莫能助啊
and commit academic suicide.
听着，我已试图阻止过他
Look, I tried to stop him.
我给了他一条出路但是不，不，不
I gave him an out,but no, no, no,
他想证明上帝没死
he wants to provethat God isn't dead.
你看，我知道我在这里，就是一个少数族裔
Look, I know I amin the minority here,
但事实上，我信仰上帝
but I actuallybelieve in God.
是，是，好吧，她是 -她还是处于进化之中
Yes, yes, well, she is--she's a work in progress.
所以，亲爱的，我认为我们最好还是转移下话题
So, darling, I think it's bestwe just change the subject.
但我只是说 -
But I'm just saying--
米娜，我礼貌地问，好吗？
Mina, I've askedpolitely, okay?.
好
Okay.
红酒烹嫩炸鸡（法式菜）快要好了
The coq au vinis almost done.
做的好
Excellent.
饭厅
T o the dining room.
一点也不像正宗的墨尔乐干红葡萄酒挂杯效果
Nothing like a nice merlotto take the edge off.
大家一起干杯
Cheers, everyone.
米娜，这酒很不对
Mina, this wine is awful.
品起来，像煮熟过的感觉
It's been cooked.
它的味道就像是晒在发霉的地下室
It tastes like it wassunning in a moldy basement.
谈论下你的《愤怒的葡萄》（美国诺贝尔奖约翰・斯坦贝克斯坦贝克代表作）
Talk about your"Grapes of Wrath."
我前几天购物之前已经买好了酒
I bought it beforeI went shopping the other day.
我回家之后
I locked it in the trunk
忘记把酒锁在汽车后备箱中了
and when I got homeI forgot about it.
嗯，我想这顿晚餐将作为一个宝贵的教训
Well, I think this dinnerserves as a valuable lesson.
正如苏格拉底在两千多年前所说
As Socrates put itover 2,000 years ago,
“Gnothi seauton.”（古希腊语，意思为认识你自己）
"Gnothi seauton."
此古希腊语恰好适合她
Looks likeit's Greek to her.
哦,这是“认识你自己”意思, 亲爱的,请认识你自己
Oh, it's "Know thyself,"darling, know thyself.
我认为其中意思是要认知到自己的局限性
Which I suggest meansknowing your own limitations.
不好意思，很抱歉
You know,if you'll all excuse me,
我帮不上什么忙
it's time forthe help to depart.
甜心
Sweetheart
有没心脏起搏器？
No pacemaker?.
其他的穿孔，也没吧？
No other piercings, right?.
是的
No.
这听起来似乎很离奇，不过，我还是要问
I know it sounds crazy,but I have to ask.
你身体内有没有金属物
If there's any ferrous metalanywhere inside your body,
因金属会受强大磁场的吸引而移动的
the magnetic fieldwill put it out, and forcibly.
在上节课，我被问了一个问题
In our last class,I was asked a question
当时我回答不出来
that I couldn't answer.
雷森迪教授指出
As Professor Radissonpointed out,
斯蒂芬・霍金是一个无神论者
Stephen Hawking is an atheist.
他还写了本叫“大设计”的书
He also wrote a bookcalled "The Grand Design"
他在书里是这么说的：
in which he saysthe following:
因为万有引力等定律，
"Because there is a lawsuch as gravity,
宇宙可以并会从无到有，自发形成.
the universe can and willcreate itself from nothing."
而说实话，当时我不知道该如何反驳这一点
And to be honest, I didn'tknow how to refute that.
我的意思是，毕竟，霍金是一个天才
I mean, after all,Hawking is clearly a genius.
但是，教数学和哲学的
But, Professor John Lennox,
兰.约翰教授（牛津大学教学）
who teaches mathematicsand philosophy
已经剖析过，那个简单的句子中
has demonstrated thatthere are not one, even two,
不至存在一个，
but three errorsof logic contained
甚至二个、三个逻辑误区.
in that one simple sentence,
而且这些都仅基于循环论证.
and it all boils downto circular reasoning.
霍金基本上是说，宇宙存在
Hawking is basically sayingthat the universe exists
是因为宇宙需要存在，
because the universeneeded to exist,
并且因为宇宙需要存在，
and because the universeneeded to exist,
因此，它自我创造.
it therefore created itself.
打个比方
It's like this.
如果我告诉你，我可以证明
If I say to youthat I can prove
午餐肉是有史以来最好吃的食物
that Spam is the best-tastingfood that's ever existed
是因为在历史中，没有食物曾有过更好的味道
because in all of history,no food has ever tasted better,
你可能会奇怪的看着我
you'd probablylook at me strange
并说我还没有证明过任何事.
and say I haven'tproven anything.
而你说这是对的
And you'd be right,
你说做的一切只是在重申原来的主张
all I've done isrestate my original claim.
而霍金声称，宇宙的自我创造
But when Hawking claimsthat the universe created itself
是因为它需要自我创造
because it neededto create itself,
然后提出关于它自我创造的原因
and then offers thatas an explanation
与自我创造的方式
as to howand why it was created,
我们不会立即承认他在做同样的事情.
we don't immediately recognizethat he's doing the same thing.
不过他确实是的.对此，兰作了进一步的剖析
But he is, promptingLennox to further comment,
“废话依然废话，
"Nonsense remains nonsense,
“即使是由著名科学家讲
"even when spokenby famous scientists
“即使一般公众
"even thoughthe general public
假定这些是科学的声称
assumes they arestatements of science."
这太目中无人了
This is the height of hubris.
你是不是想说，你一个大一新生
Are you telling methat you, a freshman,
想说斯蒂芬・霍金是错误的？
are saying thatStephen Hawking is wrong?.
不是我说，是兰.约翰说的.
No, what I'm sayingis that John Lennox,
一位数学和哲学教授，
a professor of mathematicsand philosophy,
他发现霍金教授的推理是错误的，
has found Professor Hawking'sreasoning to be faulty,
我同意他的逻辑论点.
and I agree with his logic.
但如果你不能忍受不同意
But if youcan't bear to disagree
霍金的思想
with Hawking's thinking,
那么我建议你翻到他书的第5页
then I suggest that youturn to page five of his book,
在书上，他坚持“哲学已死”，
where he insistsphilosophy is dead.
如果你如此确信
And if you're so sure
霍金教授绝无错误
of Professor Hawking'sinfallibility,
和哲学真的已死.
and philosophyreally is dead,
那么好，这门课程其实也真的没必要了.
then well, there's reallyno need for this class.
我就像他的便利设施
It's likeI'm a convenience to him,
当我满有信心时，
except for whenmy faith comes up,
他就变成恶语中伤.
then he becomesverbally abusive.
我猜他挺聪明的，
I'm guessing he's bright.
才华横溢.
Brilliant.
英俊.
Handsome.
是的.
Yes.
他的重视，使你感到特别，
And his attentionmakes you feel special,
给了你很满足的感觉.
gives you a senseof completeness.
你有没有看我的日记？
Have you beenreading my diary?.
心理学家称之为灰姑娘情结.
Psychologists call itthe Cinderella complex.
这不是我命名的，所以不要生我气.
It's not my name for it,so don't get upset with me.
男人们在方面也一样
Guys are capableof the same thing.
只不过他们没有为这个命名而已.
It's just they don'thave a name for it.
但在本质上，你的自我价值感
But in essence,you're looking for his approval
是建立在他的认同上的.
to give youa sense of self-worth
而不是源自你自己的自我认知.
instead ofgenerating it internally.
是不是大多数人也都这样呢？
Don't most people do that?.
是啊，肯定有很多人是这样的.
Y eah, a lotof people do, sure.
但是，自我形像建立在浪漫上
But, using romanceto shore up self-image
是一种不稳定的根基.
is an unstable foundation.
你相信神会犯错、有偏见、不公义？
Do you believe God's capableof error, bias, or bad judgment?.
不相信
No.
因此，他不会做错事.
So, if he's incapableof mistakes,
你是按照k的形像和样式而造的（创世记1：26）
and he made youin his likeness and image,
这显明k在乎你，对不对？
then it follows that hecares about you, right?.
对的.
Right.
到一个地步，上帝的独生子
To the pointwhere God's only Son
为你甘愿被钉在十字架上，只是为你
would willingly be crucifiedagain for you, just you,
这对你来说，还不足够
if that's whatwas necessary.
那么，假如k是如此爱你
Well, if heloves you that much,
才不要在乎你的男友是如何认为？
who cares whatyour boyfriend thinks?.
如果是错的那个人，你永远不会有任何价值.
T o the wrong person,you'll never have any worth.
但是如果是对的那人个，你就意味着一切.
But to the right person,you'll mean everything.
女士们，先生们的陪审团，
Ladies and gentlemenof the jury,
在过去的150年间，达尔文主义一直在说
for the last 1 50 years,Darwinists have been saying
在解释人的存在时，上帝是不必要的
that God is unnecessaryto explain man's existence
而进化论可取代上帝，
and that evolutionreplaces God,
但进化论只是告诉你生命拥有后
but evolution onlytells you what happens
发生了什么.
once you have life.
那么，生物是从何而来？
So, where did that somethingthat's alive come from?.
其实，达尔文从来没有真正解决这个问题.
Well, Darwinnever really addressed it.
他假设是闪电刚好击中了
He assumed maybe somelightning hit a stagnant pool
一些合适的化学物
full of the right kindof chemicals
好极了，一个活生生的生命产生了.
and bingo,a living something.
但它只是没有那么简单.
But it's just not that simple.
你看，达尔文声称，所有生物的祖先
You see, Darwin claimed that theancestry of all living things
都来自那一个单一的，简单的生物体
came from that onesingle, simple organism
再经过长时间的变异
which reproduced andwas slowly modified over time
形成我们现在看到的复杂的生命体.
into the complex life formswe view today.
这些都是他沉思后的学说
Which is why, aftercontemplating his own theory,
达尔文所说的名言：
Darwin utteredhis famous statement,
"Natura non facit saltum,"（拉丁文）
"Natura non facit saltum,"
意思是“自然界并不进行突变式发展”
meaning,"Nature does not jump."
著名的(基督徒)作家史特博.李指出
Well, as noted authorLee Strobel pointed out,
你能想像这样一幅场境，科学家们
that if you can picturethe entire 3.8 billion years
把整个38亿年历史浓缩为一天，
that scientists saylife has been around
即24小时.
as one 24-hour day,
至最后90秒时，
in the space ofjust about 90 seconds,
开始闪现大多数主要现有动物形状
most major animal groupssuddenly appear
动物群的身影
in the forms in whichthey currently hold.
并不是达尔文预测的缓慢而稳定的（进化）
Not slowly and steadilyas Darein predicted,
几乎是在瞬间.
but in evolutionary terms,almost instantly.
因此，“自然界并不进行突变式发展”
So, "nature doesnot jump" becomes
变成了“自然界产生一个巨大的飞跃”
"nature makesa giant leap."
那么，有神论者如何解释这突如其来，
So, how do theistsexplain this sudden outburst
开天辟地出现的新生物信息？
of new biological information?.
神说：“水要多多滋生有生命的物，
"And God said, 'Let the waterteem with living creatures
要有雀鸟飞在地面以上，
"'and let birdsfly above the earth
天空之中.”（创世纪1：20）
across the expanseof the sky.'
神就造出大鱼，
"So God created thegreat creatures of the sea
和水中所滋生各样有生命的动物
"and every livingand moving thing with whichthe water teems
各从其类
"according to its kind.
神看着是好的.（创世纪1：21）
And God saw that itwas good," Genesis 1 :20.
换言之，创造发生了.
In other words,creation happened
因为神说有就有,命立就立
because God saidit should happen.
甚至在我们看来似乎是
And even what looks,to our eyes,
盲目的、无目标的过程.
to be a blind,unguided process
其实从开始到结束，真的是神在控制.
could really be divinelycontrolled from start to finish.
有没有人和你一起来？
Isn't there anyone you'd liketo have here with you for this?.
没有，没有其他人.
No, there's nobody.
谎言，谎言，和更多的谎言.
Lies, lies, and more lies.
这容易忽视掉，到底你真的是不知道
It's easy to dismisswhat you don't understand
还是你不想去知道
or what you don'twant to understand.
答案应在那里，狂热的信徒所必备的装备
There it is, the defaultsetting of the Bible-thumper.
“只有你打开圣经，读圣经，
"lf only you would openthe Scripture and read,
那么你才会明白.
then you would understand."
这些都是那个勇敢、年轻的大一新生所说.
So says thebrave young freshman.
你们真是子民哪！你们死亡，智慧也就灭没了.
"For thou art wise, and withthou, all wisdom shall die,"
(约伯记12章2节)
Job 1 2, verse 2.
约伯另外还告诉我们什么？
What else does Job tell us?.
人为妇人所生，日子短少，
"For man who is bornof woman is few of days,
多有患难.（伯14:1 ）
"and full of trouble.
飞去如影，不能存留.（伯14:2后半节）
"He comes forth like a shadowand does not continue.
人也是如此，躺下不再起来.(伯14:12 )
"So man lies down,and does not rise
等到天没有了 （伯14:12前半节）
'til the heavensare no more."
好吧，至少他得到了那部分权利.
Well, at least hegot that part right.
你身上到底发生了什么？
What happened to you?.
当一个12岁大的（男孩）看到他那身患癌症，即将死去的母亲
When a 1 2-year-old watcheshis mother dying of cancer,
很自然的为了母亲的生命向上帝乞求
it's only naturalto beg God for her life.
他向那个虚幻的
He'll promise anything
在天上的阿爸父许愿
to his make-believegrandfather in the sky,
包括永远爱k、敬拜k.
including to loveand worship him forever,
只要k饶过她.
if only he will spare her.
有时候，答案是否定的.
Sometimes the answer is no.
告诉我，有一天，你失去你所爱的人，你会怎么样.
Tell that to me the dayyou lose someone you love.
她在相信那谎言中死去
She died believing a lie.
她以为死了以后，在那里会有（上帝）爱她
She died believing thatsomeone out there loved her
甚至在被k扼杀生命时，她还是怎么想的
even while he wasstrangling her to death.
一个允许这事发生的上帝，根本不值得去相信
A God who would allow thatis not worth believing in.
这就是为什么，惠顿，你会发现
That is why, Wheaton,you will find
最坚定的无神论者曾经都是基督徒，
the most committed atheistswere once Christians,
但我们对此却都视而不见.
but we tookthe blinders off.
我们看到了世界的真实情况.
We saw the worldfor what it truly is.
你看，莎士比亚说得对.
You see,Shakespeare had it right.
“人生如痴人说梦，
Life is really a taletold by an idiot,
充满着喧哗与骚动，却没有任何意义.”
full of sound and fury,and signifying nothing.
阿依莎！
Ayisha!
"k是独一的上帝，是非受生的！
"He's the one godwho has not begotten."
说！
Say it!
我命令你说！
I command you to say it!
不，爸爸.
No, Baba.
耶稣是我的主、我的拯救者，k为了救我脱离罪孽而受死.
Jesus is my Lord and Savior andhe died to save me from my sins.
不！
No!
因 我 知      演唱    特里西娅.布鲁克
Tricia Brock singing  "What I Know"
信靠、信靠，
?Carry on, carry on?
因我知祢是我的真神，
?What I know is you,my God, are real?
不管我处何境，祢总不离弃我，
?No matter how I feel,you've never let me go?
我且也知永不会有这天，
?And what I knowis there will never be a day?
因你不只是单向我吹气的神.
?You aren'tjust a breath away?
因经过这一切，我要保守我所知，
?And through it allI've gotta hold to what I know?
更要保守我所知，
?Gonna holdto what I know?
因我知，
?What I know?
因我知.
对延迟发表我的采访这事，很抱歉.
Sorry for the delayin posting my interview.
这是艰难的一周.
It's been a rough week.
什么都让我碰上了.
When I finally caught up to--
新头衔
New post.
癌症患者.
I have cancer.
艾米就要死了.
Amy is going to die.
不！
No!
杰弗里，我需要和你谈谈.
Jeffrey, I needto talk to you.
你知道有些东西我很在乎的.
You know howI feel about that.
在校园里，我是雷森迪教授，好吗？
On campus, I'mProfessor Radisson, okay?.
那么，后来他就声称达而文所说的是错的.
So, then he claims that Dawkinsis the one who was in error,
好像达尔文认为 -
as if Dawkins thought--
杰弗里，我要离开你了.
Jeffrey, I'm leaving you.
对不起 - 打扰一下.
Excuse me.
什么？
What?.
你说什么？
What are you saying?.
我要离开你.
I'm leaving you.
你不能这么做.
You can't do that.
我是不会接受的.
I won't accept it.
对不起.
I'm sorry.
我说我不接受.
I said I don'taccept that.
我不允许.
I won't allow it.
我知道，我听见你说了，但这不是你说了算.
I know, I heard you,but it's not your choice.
再见，杰弗里.
Good bye, Jeffrey.
她隐藏信仰有多久了？
How long has shebeen hiding her faith?.
大约一年.
About a year.
我甚至不能想像她要承受什么
I can't even imaginewhat she must be feeling.
这就是你的战壕 ，大卫.
You asked to bein the trenches, David.
我在做什么，大卫牧师？
What have I done,Pastor Dave?.
我已失去了一切.
I've lost everything.
我做错了什么事情？
What if I madea mistake?.
阿依莎，你已经展示出了惊人的勇气.
Ayisha, you've displayedan amazing amount of courage
在你的信仰上站立起来了.
by standing upfor your faith.
上帝知道你所承受的，k会记念这事的.
God knows the risks you've takenand he will honor that.
我不认为我可以做到这一点.
I don't thinkI can do this.
阿依莎，我们都跟你在一起.
We're here for you,Ayisha.
你 - 你读过保罗书信？
Are you - have you readof the Apostle Paul?.
他说，我知道怎样处卑贱，(腓4：12-13）
He said, "l knowwhat it is to have little,
也知道怎样处丰富.
and I know what it isto have plenty.
随事随在，
ln any and all circum stances,
我都得了秘诀.
l have learned the secretof being well-fed
或饱足、或饥饿，
and of being hungry,
或有余、或缺乏.
of having plent yand of being in need.
凡事都能做.
I can do all things"
我靠着那加给我力量的.
"Through Christ who strengthens me."
是的.
Right.
你并不孤单，阿依莎.
You're not alone, Ayisha.
你会好起来的.
You're gonna be okay.
我让你在我的课台上侃侃而谈，
I made a mistake with you,
胡加宣传，
Ietting you speakin front of my classroom
现在看来，对我来说意味着是一个错误.
and spewyour propaganda.
但今天，我们要去改变一些规则
But today, we're gonnachange things up a bit.
罪恶
Evil.
现在,据说“ 罪恶”是无神论者攻击基督教信仰最有力的武器
Now, it's been said that evilis atheism's most potent weapon
不过，确实也是如此.
against the Christian faith,and it is.
毕竟，存在罪恶牵引出了另一个问题
After all, the very existenceof evil begs the question,
如果上帝是全善、上帝是全能的，
"lf God is all-goodand God is all-powerful,
怎么会允许罪恶存在？
why does he allowevil to exist?. "
在其核心的答案是非常简单的，“自由意志”
The answer at its core isremarkably simple: free will.
上帝允许罪恶产生，是因为“自由意志”
God allows evil to existbecause of free will.
从基督教的角度来看，神容忍罪恶在这个世界上
From the Christian standpoint,God tolerates evil in this world
是暂时的，有这样一天，
on a temporary basisso that one day,
那些真正选择爱k的
those who chooseto love him freely
将与k一同住在天堂，摆脱罪恶的轧制，
will dwell with him in heaven,free from the influence of evil,
从而具有良性的自由意志.
but with theirfree will in tact.
换句话说，上帝对罪恶的态度，
In other words,God's intention concerning evil
就是有一天摧毁它.
is to one day destroy it.
真好，太方便了.
Well, how convenient.
“有一天，我将摆脱在世界上所有的罪恶.
"One day, I will get ridof all the evil in the world.
“但在那之前，你只需要处理所有的战争，
"But until then, you just haveto deal with all the wars,
“和大屠杀，海啸，贫困，饥饿，艾滋病.
"and Holocausts, tsunamis,poverty, starvation, and AlDS.
美好的生活.
Have a nice life."
接下来，他通过道德的绝对性来教育我们.
Next, he'll be lecturing uson moral absolutes.
但是，为什么不呢？
But why not?.
雷森迪教授，谁显然是一个无神论者，
Professor Radisson,who's clearly an atheist,
不相信道德的绝对性，
doesn't believein moral absolutes,
但他的核心教学大纲说，他计划在
but his core syllabus sayshe plans to give us an exam
在最后一周对我们进行考试.
during finals week.
现在，我敢说，如果我设法为了得到一个“A”
Now, I'm betting thatif I manage to get an "A"
在考试中作弊，
on the exam by cheating,
他就会突然用上基督徒的语调,说：
he'll suddenly startsounding like a Christian,
坚持“欺骗是错误的”，
insisting it's wrongto cheat,
我应该知道这点.
that I should haveknown that.
然而，他的依据是什么？
And yet,what basis does he have?.
如果我的所做所为，是为了帮助我成功
If my actions are calculatedto help me succeed,
那么，为什么我不应该执行呢？
then why shouldn'tI perform them?.
对于基督徒来说，道德的标准，
For Christians,the fixed point of morality,
什么是对，什么是错，
what constitutesright and wrong,
是一条直线，最终直接向上帝（负责)
is a straight linethat leads directly back to God.
哦，所以你说，我们需要一个上帝是具有道德性的，
Oh, so you're saying thatwe need a God to be moral,
一个无神论具有道德是不可能的.
that a moral atheistis an impossibility.
不是的，但没有上帝，道德没有任何真正的意义.
No, but with no God, uu
我的意思是，甚至不存在
I mean, there'snot even a standard
道德行为的标准.
of what moral behavior is.
对于基督徒来说，说谎，欺骗，偷窃 -
For Christians,lying, cheating, stealing--
拿我举例，我偷拿了并非我自己赚取学分等级
in my example, stealinga grade I didn't earn--
是被禁止的.
are forbidden.
它是盗窃的一种形式.
It's a form of theft.
但是，如果上帝不存在，
But if God does not exist,
陀思妥耶夫斯基（俄国作家）的名言所说:
as Dostoyevskyfamously pointed out,
“如果上帝不存在，人可以任意妄为.”
"lf God does not exist,then everything is permissible."
虽可妄为，但毫无意义.
And not only permissible,but pointless.
如果雷森迪教授是正确的，那么所有一切，
If Professor Radisson is right,then all of this,
我们所有的奋斗，我们的辩论，
all of our struggle,our debate,
无论我们在这里决定了什么，也是毫无意义的.
whatever we decide hereis meaningless.
我的意思是，我们的生命和我们的死亡，
I mean, our livesand ultimately our deaths
比金鱼也好不了那里去.
have no more consequencethan that of a goldfish.
这是荒谬的.
This is ridiculous.
所以，毕竟你的讨论，
So, after all your talk,
你所说的这一切无非归结为：
you're saying that it allcomes down to choice:
选择相信或不相信.
believe or don't believe.
对的，那些就是我想说的，
That's right,that's all there is.
那些我想说的也曾发生过，
That's allthere's ever been.
你我位置之间的唯一区别：
The only difference betweenyour position and my position
就是你拿走他们的选择.
is that you take awaytheir choice.
你要求他们选择的标题就是:"我不相信”
You demand that they choose thebox marked, "l don't believe."
是的，因为我想释放他们.
Y es, becauseI want to free them.
因为宗教就像是一 -
Because religionis like a--
它就像一记父母遗传
it's like a mind virusthat parents have passed on
给他们孩子的病毒
down to their children,
而基督教就是那最糟糕的病毒.
and Christianityis the worst virus of all.
趁我们软弱、生病、无助时，
It slowly creepsinto our lives
它慢慢地潜入我们的生命.
when we're weakor sick or helpless.
因此，宗教就是像一种疾病？
So, religionis like a disease?.
是.是的，它感染了一切.
Yes. Yes, it infectseverything.
它是理性的敌人.
It's the enemy of reason.
理性？
Reason?.
教授，你在很久以前就没理性了.
Professor, you left reasona long time ago.
你在这儿上的不是哲学课.
What you're teaching hereisn't philosophy.
它甚至也不是无神论课.
It's not evenatheism anymore.
你所教的是反神论课.
What you're teachingis antitheism.
这还不够，你自己不相信.
It's not enoughthat you don't believe.
你还能让我们一起跟你不相信.
You need all of usto not believe with you.
你为什么不承认事实？
Why don't youadmit the truth?.
你只是让他们陷入你的原始迷信中.
You just want to ensnare themin your primitive superstition.
我要的是让他们做出自己的选择.
What I want is for themto make their own choice.
这才是上帝想要的（赐自由意志原因）
That's what God wants.
你不知道我有多享受你将要的失败.
You have no idea how muchI'm gonna enjoy failing you.
哦，但谁才是你真正希望失败的对像，教授？
Yeah, but who are you reallylooking to fail, Professor?.
我还是神？
Me or God?.
你恨上帝？
Do you hate God?.
这甚至都不是一个问题.
That's not evena question.
好了，你为什么恨上帝？
Okay, why do youhate God?.
这是荒谬的.
This is ridiculous.
你为什么恨上帝？请回答这个问题.
Why do you hate God?.Answer the question.
你已经看到了科学的论据.
You've seen the scienceand the arguments.
科学都在支持k的存在.
Science supportshis existence.
你知道事情的真相.
You know the truth.
那么，你为什么恨k？
So, why do you hate him?.
为什么？
Why?.!
这是一个很简单的问题，教授.
It's a very simplequestion, Professor.
你为什么恨上帝？
Why do you hate God?.
因为k把我身边的一切都夺走了
Because he tookeverything away from me.
是的，我恨上帝.
Yes, I hate God.
我对k只有恨.
All I have for himis hate.
你怎么能恨一个人，如果他们不存在？
How can you hate someoneif they don't exist?.
已经证明不了什么.
You've proven nothing.
也许不是.
Maybe not.
他们可以去选择.
They get to choose.
是上帝已死？
Is God dead?.
还是上帝未死.
God is not dead.
上帝未死.
God's not dead.
上帝未死.上帝未死.
God's not dead.God's not dead.
上帝未死.上帝未死.上帝未死.
God's not dead.God's not dead.God's not dead.
乔什！
Josh!.
乔什，乔什！
Josh. Josh!
你对上帝未死的论证，
Your decision to proveGod is not dead
极大地影响了我.
has affected me greatly.
对此，我很高兴.
I'm glad.w
是的，它已经改变了一切.
Yes, and it haschanged everything.
我已经决定要跟从耶稣.
I've decidedto follow Jesus.
这很好，马丁.
That's great, Martin.
嘿，你知道吗？
Hey, you know what?.
你得看看这个.
You've gottacheck this out.
- 好.- 来吧.
- Okay.- Come on.
我为什么要带上我的手提箱呢？
Why did I have tobring my suitcase?.
没带上，显示你缺少信心.
Not bringing itwould show a lack of faith.
哦，慈爱的天父，求祢让这辆车可以启动吧！
Oh merciful Father,please allow this car to start.
阿门.
Amen.
就这样？
That's it?.
为什么，难道你有一个比
Why, do you have a better"Lord, please make my car run"
“主啊，求祢让这辆能跑”更好的祝福
blessing that you know?.
没有
No.
那么，就让我们试一下吧.
So then,let's give it a try.
好.
Okay.
不，不，不，不.
No, no, no, no.
先把我们的行李放在后备箱.
Put our bagsin the trunk first.
大卫，我们用我们的整个生活去实践信仰.
David, we spend our entire livestalking about faith.
现在，我要你显示你的信心.
Now I'm asking youto show faith.
好.
Okay.
- 难以置信.- 不，信心.
- Unbelievable.- No. Faith.
- 上帝是良善的.- 一直.
- God is good.- All the time.
- 在一直中？- 上帝是良善的.
- And all the time?.- God is good.
我甚至都不知道我在这里要干什么？
I don't even knowwhat I'm doing here.
我的意思是，你甚至连我是谁都不知道？
I mean, it's not likeyou even know who I am.
在你的整个人生中，
You prayed and believed
你一直祷告而且相信.
your whole life,
从来没有做错任何事，
never done anything wrong,
在你却在这里.
and here you are.
你是我所知的那个最好的人，而我是最差的.
You're the nicest person I know,I am the meanest.
你有老年痴呆症，我的生活却是完美的.
You have dementia,my life is perfect.
请向我解释，
Explain that to me.
有时，魔鬼允许
Sometimes the devilallows people
人们无忧无虑的生活，
to live a lifefree of trouble
是因为它不希望人们转向神.
'cause he doesn't want themturning to God.
你的罪像牢房，除此之外都很美好、舒适，
Your sin is like a jail cell,except it's all nice and comfy,
而且似乎没有任何必要离开.
and there doesn't seem to beany need to leave.
大门是敞开的
The door's wide open
有一天，时候将到
'til one day,time runs out,
窄门猛一关闭
and the cell doorslams shut
突然...为时已晚.
and suddenly...it's too late.
你说你是谁？
Who did you say you were?.
我真不敢相信，
I can't believe this.
这车真的启动了，
The car actually starts
现在我们被这帮信徒累得够呛，
and now we're beingdone-in by believers.
我认为这还是不错的.
I think it's beautiful.q
你那些智慧的话请不要再说了，
Please,no more words of wisdom.
但我很高兴看到
But I'm just happy to see
所有这些人去向耶稣唱歌
all these peoplegoing to sing about Jesus.
快开！
Move!.
你们好，先生们.
Hello, gentlemen.
我能帮到你什么吗？
Can I help you?.
我是艾美.我是“新左派”专栏作者.
I'm Amy Ryan.I write "The New Left."
你好？
Michael Tait.How are you?.
我们预约安排过？
Did we schedule this?.
没有，其实我发现，最好的访问就是脱稿.
No, I actually find that thebest interviews are unscripted.
因此，在几分钟内，你们就要去那里，
So, in a few minutes, youguys are gonna go out there
你们将要去唱上帝和耶稣，
and you're gonna singabout God and Jesus
好像他们就像跟你我如此真实一样
as if they're as realas you and me.
你们怎么能做到这样？
How can you do that?.
好了，对我们来说，神是为真实的.
Well, to us,they are as real.
事实上，更是如此.
As a matter of fact,even more so.
我的意思是，我们存在于此时此地.
I mean, we existin the here and now.
神是永远存在的.想想这一点.
They've existed forever.Think about that.
是的，你知道，太初有道，
Y eah, you know,in the beginning was the Word.
道与　神同在，道就是　神.（约1：1）
The Word was with Godand the Word was God.
那么，我明白了.当你遭受到抨击时，
So, I see.So when you're pressed,
你引用了一堆古老且胡写的文章，说
you quote a bunch ofancient scribblings and say,
“不用担心，这一切都在那里.”
"Don't worry,it's all in there."vfb
好吧，这些可能是古老的，但并不是胡写的.
Well, they may be ancient,but they're not scribblings.
我的意思是，我们相信上帝给了我们一份说明手册.
I mean, we believe Godgave us an instruction manual,
告诉我们力量的源泉在那里，
and it's wherewe draw our strength
还有我们的盼望在那里.
and it's wherewe find our hope.
那里，请告诉我你的盼望在那里？
So, where do youfind your hope?.
我正在死去.
I'm dying.
嘿，艾米，你没有在这里恶心我们吧，是吗？
Hey Amy, you're not hereto trash us, are you?.
我想这些事你曾经都做过吧.
I think that's whatyou might have done,
但是我还是挺纳闷你在这里，
but I think you're herekinda wondering,
有点希望这种东西是真实的,是不?.
kinda hoping that this stuffis for real, aren't you?.
你怎么知道？
How do you know that?.
我只是觉得，这就是上帝在说，
I just felt that that'swhat God was saying,
k只是想让你知道.
and he just wantedyou to know it.
- 我不能
That's I can't
是的，他只是鼓手.
Y eah, and he'sjust the drummer.
追逐太阳      演唱    Safe Haven 乐队
Safe Haven singing"Chasing the Sun"
?And we never really didwhat we're told?
?And we'll say we were dumband all alone?
?But we're stillchasing the sun?
?We'll say we were youngand full of hope?
?And we never really didwhat we're told?
?And we'll say we were dumband all alone?
?But we're stillchasing the sun?
?One day, we'll fadebut we'll never forget?
我最亲爱的儿子，
My dearest son,
言语无法表达我对你的爱，
"words cannot expressthe love I have for you
和我心中的悲伤，
"or the sorrow in my heart
我知道将永远无法看到你成长的过程，
"knowing that I will neverbe able to see you grow up
并履行上帝在你生命的计划，
"and fulfill God's planfor your life.
想到离开你那一刻，我的心都要碎了，
"My heart is brokenat the thought of leaving you.
但我知一切都在上帝的掌管中，
"l know God is in control.
k的道路高过我们的道路，
"His ways arehigher than our ways
k的意念高过我们的意念.（赛55：9）
"and his thoughtsare higher than our thoughts.
生活要有力量，靠主常喜乐，
"Live life to the fullest andremain in the joy of the Lord.
你永远留在我心中.
"You will foreverbe in my heart.
我爱你.妈妈.
I love you.Mom."
嘿，这是米娜.
Hey, it's Mina.
对不起，我无法接听你电话.请留言.
Sorry I missed your call.Leave a message.
米娜，我是杰弗里.
Mina, it's Jeffrey.
请给我打电话.
Please call me.
嘿，伙计们，我们要上台表演了.
Hey guys,we're a-go for the show.
嘿，史蒂夫.请给我们一分钟，哥们.
Hey Steve,give us a minute, buddy.
这有点重要.
This is kinda important.
- 谢谢你们.- 谢谢.
- Thanks guys.- Thanks.
我们为你做一个简短的祷告？
Can we prayfor you real quick?.
你介意吗？
Do you mind?.
好.
Cool.
亲爱的上帝，我们不知道祢在艾米生命中的计划，主啊，
Dear God, we don't knowyour plan for Amy, Lord,
但我们今晚向祢祈求，求你拯救她，
but we're asking you wouldsave her tonight, Lord.
改变她，洁净她，给她一个全新的开始，主.
Change her, cleanse her,give her a fresh start, Lord.
让她知道她是被祢所爱的，祢也视她为至宝.
Let her know that she's loved,and more importantly,
她是被祢这位宇宙间的主宰所爱，
that she is loved by you,the Master of the universe.
主啊，在她前行的路途中祢要给她加添力量，
Give her strength forthe journey ahead, Lord,
让她在心中真认识祢，向她的心说话，神啊，
and let her know in her heart,God, speak to her,
她所行的路上，祢都与她同在，
that you're gonna be with herevery step of the way.
如此祷告，奉耶稣圣名求，
We pray this, Jesus,in your holy name.
阿门.
Amen.
是啊.
Yeah.
嘿，伙计们，我们得赶紧.
Hey guys, we gotta roll.
好，你没事吧，艾米？
Cool, you gonna beokay, Amy?.
你好吗？
You good?.
The King Is Coming    演唱    纽斯男孩
NowsBoys singing "The King Is Coming"
有空处，
?Make a way for?
有空处为王，
?Make a way for the King?
王已降临，
?The King is coming?
空乏心灵被填满，
?Empty heartsare filling up?
恶行全被撤毁，
?Wicked waysare coming undone?
众目期待为祢，
?Every eyeis looking out for you?
城市的灯光正被点燃，
?City lightsare burning out?
自由的歌声响彻云宵，
?Freedom's songis ringing loud?
沉睡的生命被你们的歌声唤醒，
?Dead men waking upto the sound of you?
我们的心同声齐唱，
?And all our heartscan sing?
?All our hearts can sing?
有空处，
?Make a way for?
有空处为王，
?Make a way for the King?
王已降临，
?The King is coming?
因此，有空处，
?So, make a way for?
有空处，
?Make a way for?
有空处为王，
?Make a way for the King?
哦，那真完美.
Oh, that's perfect.
多么想念阳光普照和晴朗的天空.
So much for sunnyand clear skies.
叫救护车！
Call an ambulance!
不要动.
Don't move.
他的肋骨被撞碎.
His ribs are crushed.
他的肺部大出血.
His lungsare filling with blood.
他没有多长时间了.
He doesn't have long.
你确定？
Are you sure?.
是的.
Yeah.
不要动.
Don't move.
我不能死.
I can't die.
我还没准备好.
I'm not ready.
你知道耶稣吗？
Do you know Jesus?.
我是一个无神论者.
I'm an atheist.
我相信这是上帝的怜悯是把我带到这里，现在.
I believe it's God's mercythat brought me here right now.
我要死了.
I'm dying.
你怎么能称之为怜悯？
How can youcall that mercy?.
因为这车可以可能立刻撞死你.
Because that car could havekilled you instantly.
我敢肯定，你现在真巴不得是那样.
And I'm sure right nowyou probably wish that it did,
但我在这里告诉你，这是一份礼物
but I'm here to tell youthat it's a gift
你不相信的那位上帝，
'cause the Godthat you don't believe in
现在在给你一次机会，
has given youanother chance,
一次改变你最终答案的机会.
another chanceto change your final answer.
我并不想死，我很害怕.
I don't want to die,but I'm so scared.
愿主赐下各样安慰，
If it's any consolation,so was Jesus.
他很害怕，他一直在流血.
He was so scared,he sweat blood.
他问天父是否会放弃他.
He asked the Father if itcould be removed from him,
答案是否定的.
but the answer was no.
他已经说过很多次“不”，
He says no a lot.
k已经给了我们寻求的答案，
He gives us the answerswe'd ask for
因我们知k知晓万事，
if we knewwhat he knows.
天怎样高过地，
"'For as the heavensare higher than the earth,
照样，我的道路高过你们的道路，
"so are my ways higherthan your ways,
我的意念高过你们的意念.“这是主耶和华说的”.（赛55：9）
and my thoughts are higher thanyour thoughts,' says the Lord."
没错.
Exactly.
所以，问题是 -留在我身边.
So, the question is--stay with me.
留在我身边.
Stay with me.
你是否愿意把信心建立在耶稣基督身上？
Are you willing to putyour faith in Jesus Christ?.
你是否愿意把握住这个机会？
Are you willingto take that chance?.
是.
Y es.
神愿意赦免你所有的罪孽，
God is willing to forgive youof your sins, all of them,
如果你接受了k的儿子，并邀请k进入你的生命
if you accept his Sonand ask him into your life.
现在你所要做的仅是接受k儿子
That's all you have to dois just accept his Son.
立刻接受k的慈爱和赦免,
Accept his love and receivehis forgiveness right now.
你接受k为你的救主吗？
Do you accept himas Lord and Savior?.
是的，我接受.
Yes, I accept.
没事的.
It's alright.
在几分钟内，你会更多地的明白上帝比我好，
In a few minutes, you're gonnaknow more about God than I do,
比这里的其他人都好.
or anybody else here does.
没事，没事.
It's okay, it's okay.
请看我后面的屏幕
If you check outthe screens behind me,
我有一个好朋友要给大家一份非常特殊的信息
we have a very special messagefrom a very good friend.
嘿，我是威利・罗伯逊，
Hey, I'm Willie Robertson,
代表罗伯逊家庭向大家问候，
speaking on behalfof the Robertson family.
我和大家想让你知道，
Me and the gangwanted to let you know
我们听到的消息，
we've heard in the news
在校园发生一些争吵，
that there's been a bit ofa squabble down there on campus.
你的一个教授坚持认为，上帝已死.
One of your professors insistedthat God is dead.
嗯，我很高兴地宣布上帝已死的报道，
Well, I'm happy to announcethat the reports of God's death
真是夸大其词.
were greatly exaggerated.
现在，让我问你一个问题.
Now, let meask you a question.
你带着手机吗？
Have you got yourcell phones on you?.
好.
Good.
那么，当我们接下来这曲歌在演唱时
Alright, now whilethis next song is playing,
我希望每个人都打开你们的通讯录，
I want everyoneto go to their contacts
向你们通讯录中的每一个人
and click oneverybody you know1668tm
发送3个简单的词语：
and text themthree simple words:
“上帝未死（God's not dead)”
"God's not dead."
你们今天这里有10000人，
And there's1 0,000 of you out there,
每个人都知道约100人.
and everyone knowsabout 1 00 people.
这就有100万条信息在你们那里.
That's a million messagesright there.
在接下来的3分钟
A million times we're gonna tellJesus that we love him
我们可以告诉耶稣100万次我们爱k，
in the next 3 minutes.
那个拿起战书去I卫神荣耀的年轻人
And for the young manwho took up the gauntlet
你知道我所说的是谁
to defend God's honor,and you know who you are,
我只能想象神悦纳你所做时的笑容.
I can only imagine the smileyou put on God's face.
现在轮到你们了.
This one goes out to you.p
你是那个为神的荣耀去I卫的那个人
It was you, wasn't it?.
是不是你？
The one who defended God?.
是啊.
Yeah.
你怎么知道的？
How did you know?.
我听到你在食堂的谈话.
I heard you talkingin the cafeteria.
真正的危险，是考验一个人信仰真实与否的试金石，对不对？
Only a real risk teststhe quality of a belief, right?.
Like a Lion    演唱    纽斯男孩
NowsBoys singing "Like a Lion"
让爱发光，带给死亡复生，
?Let love explodeand bring the dead to life?
如此大爱，定有生命翻转，
?A love so bold to seea revolution somehow?
让爱发光，带给死亡复生，
?Let love explodeand bring the dead to life?
如此大爱，定有生命翻转，
?A love so bold to seea revolution somehow?
现在我在祢里面得自由，
?Now I'm lostin your freedom?
我也要靠主胜过这个世界，
?And this worldI'll overcome?
我的上帝未死，k肯定活着，
?My God's not dead,he's surely alive?
k居住在里面，如狮咆哮，
?He's living on the inside,roaring like a lion?
我的上帝没有死，k肯定还活着，
?My God's not dead,he's surely alive?
k居住在里面，如狮咆哮，
?He's living on the inside,roaring like a lion?
咆哮，k在咆哮，如狮咆哮，
?Roaring, he's roaring,roaring like a lion?
让希望出现，使黑暗隐藏
?Let hope arise andmake the darkness hide?
我的信心是死的，
?My faith is dead?
我需要一场复兴
?I need a resurrectionsomehow?
现在我在祢里面得自由，
?Now I'm lostin your freedom?
我也要靠主胜过这个世界，
?And this worldI'll overcome?
我的上帝未死，k肯定活着，
?My God's not dead,he's surely alive?
k居住在里面，如狮咆哮，
?He's living on the inside,roaring like a lion?
我的上帝未死，k肯定活着，
?My God's not dead,he's surely alive?
k居住在里面，如狮咆哮，
?He's living on the inside,roaring like a lion?
咆哮，k在咆哮，如狮咆哮，
?Roaring, he's roaring,roaring like a lion?
k的咆哮，k的咆哮，
?He's roaring,he's roaring?
愿天势轰鸣、烈火降下，
?Let heaven roarand fire fall?
复兴的声音震动大地
?Come shake the groundwith the sound of revival?
愿天势轰鸣、烈火降下，
?Let Heaven roarand fire fall?
复兴的声音震动大地
?Come shake the groundwith the sound of revival?
今晚在这里发生的事，是值得庆祝的.
What happened here tonightis a cause for celebration.
疼痛，是短短的几分钟，但现在，
Pain, yes, for justa few moments, but now,
想想在天堂里的喜乐.
think aboutthe joy in heaven.
我的上帝未死，k肯定活着，
?My God's not dead,he's surely alive?
k居住在里面，如狮咆哮，
?He's living on the inside,roaring like a lion?
我的上帝未死，k肯定活着，
?My God's not dead,he's surely alive?
k居住在里面，如狮咆哮，
?He's living on the inside,roaring like a lion?
上帝未死，k肯定活着，
?God's not dead,he's surely alive?
k居住在里面，如狮咆哮，
?He's living on the inside,roaring like a lion?
上帝未死，k肯定活着，
?God's not dead,he's surely alive?
k居住在里面，如狮咆哮，
?He's living on the inside,roaring like a lion?
咆哮，k在咆哮，如狮咆哮，
?Roaring, he's roaring,roaring like a lion?
?He's roaring, he's roaring,roaring like a lion?
如狮咆哮
?Roaring like a lion?
我们的神是活的神
?Our God is alive?
发信息告诉所有你认识的人
上帝是活的神
This is the Time    演唱    Super chick 乐队
Super chick singing "This is the Time"
?This is a story of your life,a movie starring you?
?What's the next scene have for you to do?.?
?Leave the dishes in the sink,leave your fear there too?
?Live the story you would write for you?
?Say, hey, hey,wake your heart?
?And break, break,break apart?
?The walls that keep you from being you?
?And walk, walk towards the light?
?And don't stop'til you live your life?
?Like someone died for you?
?This is the time to try?
?Just step out,your life is waiting?
?And as you fall,you'll find that you can fly?
?This is the time to try?
?Just step out,your life is waiting?
?And as you fall,you'll find that you can fly?
?You can find a million words to build a wall of fear?
?Safe behind that wall, imprisoned here?
?Take that someday step today to who you're meant to be?
?And turn your dream to plans so you can breathe?
?Say, hey, hey,wake your heart?
?And break, break,break apart?
?The walls that keep you from being you?
?And walk, walk towards the light?
?And don't stop'til you live your life?
?Like someone died for you?
?This is the time to try?
?Just step out,your life is waiting?
?And as you fall,you'll find that you can fly?
?Ask anyone whose time is up?
?What they'd give for what you've got?
?And how they'd live your life?
?Live like your life's worth dying for?
?You just walked out that prison door?
?And you'll know how to live your life?
?This is the time to try?
?Just step out,your life is waiting?
?And as you fall,you'll find that you can fly?
?This is the time to try?
?Just step out,your life is waiting?
?And as you fall,you'll find that you can fly?
?This is the time to try?
?Just step out,your life is waiting?
?And as you fall,you'll find that you can fly?